<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full answer to the depositions and to all other the pretences and arguments whatsoever concerning the birth of the Prince of Wales the intreague thereof detected, the whole design being set forth, with the way and manner of doing it : whereunto is annexed a map or survey engraven of St. James Palace, and the convent there : describing the place wherein it is supposed the true mother was delivered : with the particular doors and passages through which the child was convey'd to the queens bed-chamber.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40606</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8959113</idno>
  <idno type="VID">42098</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264216121</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25436</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08959113</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1284:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full answer to the depositions and to all other the pretences and arguments whatsoever concerning the birth of the Prince of Wales the intreague thereof detected, the whole design being set forth, with the way and manner of doing it : whereunto is annexed a map or survey engraven of St. James Palace, and the convent there : describing the place wherein it is supposed the true mother was delivered : with the particular doors and passages through which the child was convey'd to the queens bed-chamber.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 21 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Simon Burgis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">James, --  Prince of Wales, 1688-1766.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42098:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42098:1"/>
            <p>A Full Answer TO THE DEPOSITIONS; And to all other the Pretences and Arguments whatsoever, Concerning the Birth of the PRINCE of WALES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Intreague thereof detected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole design being set forth, with the way and manner of doing it.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed, A Map or Survey Engraven of St. <hi>James</hi>'s Palace, and the Convent there: Describing the Place wherein it is suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the true Mother was delivered: With the particular Doors and Passages through which the Child was convey'd TO THE QUEENS Bed-Chamber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Simon Burgis.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:42098:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42098:2"/>
            <head>THE Authors Apology.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Copy, or rather Imperfect Notes, by which the following Sheets were Printed, being obtained from me by Surprize, are neither so curious as I would have made them, had I ever intended such a Publication; nor indeed, so Accurate as things of this Nature require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For being at first only designed to be presented to the Committees, that should be appointed to look into the Birth of the pretended Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the more Imperfect, by how much more time I thought I should have had, e're such Committee sate, to transcribe and amend them; and the more confused, in regard that there is not occasion of such nice Demonstration, to those of such quick Apprehensions, as undoubtedly our Worthy Representatives are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet how many and how great soever the Imperfections and Errata's are, the Matters of Fact, and Conclusions thereon, are sufficiently evincing, plain and perceptible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I have failed in any Point or Assertion whatsoever, I shall readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my Errour, by publickly retracting the same, and shall think my self highly obliged to any person for his kind Information and Rebuke; all which I do faithfully promise to expugn, alter, or amend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My design (and the Publishers too) being far from prejudice, partiallity, or hopes of gain, wishing it may, though in such a ragged Dress, do as much good by keeping the Weak from being Imposed on, by designing men, as was at first intended by reminding the Committees, as with a Breviate of</hi> Memorandums, <hi>and to shew them that of all the many Pretences, by which it is indeavoured to varnish the Childs Birth, not one is feazible; that they are not only false and frivolous at first sight, but when Explicated, the very signs, the very steps and methods of an Imposture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any one shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>for the disadvantage of the Dress Reflect, or Animadvert thereon, 'twill be highly unfair and disingenuous, since I cannot defend that to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>less, which my Well-meaning Friends have so curtailed, resolving in the next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dition, I will defend it against the most Malevolent Sophister what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever; for indeed, this Book should not have appeared in the World as it does, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by any means possibly have hinder'd it, not knowing of its being in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till Four Sheets were Printed off, and was strangely surprized, when I say it in an Ayre and bace so Foreign to what I designed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42098:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Publishers and Printers being unacquainted with my Hand Writing, and the haste they were in to get it so far e're I knew it, that it might of necessity be Published, has occasioned many gross and unpardonable faults, with such large Omissions, that in some places the Sense is rendred Inextricable; the chief (it being endless to take notice of all) being these following:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 13. <hi>Column</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 45. <hi>for</hi> Justice should so prevail as to work on them some remorse, <hi>read</hi> Justice should not prevail nor work on them any remorse.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 34. If she urges the bigness of the Queens Belly, nothing more easie (as I have shewed before) to deceive her: <hi>Which Parenthesis should be left out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 46. No Midwife can see of what Sex the Child is before the Burthen is drawn out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas my Notes, which the Printer mistook, give it thus,</hi> That the Queen being covered so, that the Midwife could not see the Child nor Queen, the Child being not parted when Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> said it was a Boy; 'tis evident that she could not know any such thing, had the Queen been really in those Circumstances of a Delivery, and therefore her so saying was by a fore-knowledge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42098:3"/>
            <head>THE Introductory Discourse.</head>
            <p>IN the pursuit of this Discourse I shall be forced to make use of all publick as well as private circumstances, which however at first sight may seem unvaluable, yet are necessary to the finding out of this hidden secret, and to bring it to the light. The more arguments we overthrow the less can be rallyed up in the designing heads of those men, who have either the little wit or honesty to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Chimera of a Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> or any confused Ideas to uphold it.</p>
            <p>I will gather up all the circumstances of this birth, and will here renumerate what others have perhaps carelessly or ignorantly past by, and not inspected into the artifice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to detect it; and weighing some, will shew you their falseness and inconsistencies, then leading you to others, which you finding no otherwise, will I hope be obliged to go through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, wherein nothing can be found but ridiculous, incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and impertinent pretences: And finally, the whole will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate the improbability, nay, impossibility of this Childs being really born of the Queen: And if I prove that, I think the matter will be sufficiently refuted, since the question is not whose it is if it be not the Queens.</p>
            <p>I must confess I should not bandy these things about to the dishonour of a King, were they not made use of to the defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a Princess of her Birthright, and upon which the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents are so vehemently resolved, that they catch like drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men at every trifle, to uphold their weak and suffocated pretences.</p>
            <p>The first part of the design, concerning Milk, Bigness and likelihood of Miscarriage, had not craft nor art, so as to make them appear real on the test of a nice scrutiny; but was only carried on by insipid &amp; frivolous pretences, and the downright denial (on all requests whatsoever) of exposing any thing to be inspected. Now if their bare words can so far work on peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as to make them believe this is a true Birth, and that on such trifling circumstances, notwithstanding this infallible rule, <hi>viz.</hi> That they would have shewn (for their own interest) undeniable matters, had her Majesty been really with Child. If then, I say, we are gull'd with such pretences, we are in a very fair way to have <hi>Mahomet</hi> pawn'd upon us for a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, since the word of a <hi>Mussulman</hi> was ever of more validity than that of a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, or Rascally Protestant.</p>
            <p>The unperceived carrying of the Child into the Queens Bed, was not so much owing to a cleanly conveyance, as to their unjust proceedings, by withstanding the directions of the Law, which decrees, <hi>That the Woman shall for several Months before, notifie the Room where She intends</hi>
               <note place="margin">25. <hi>Lib. Digest. Titul.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect. De Inspiciendo ventre.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>to be Delivered, which Room shall be searched, and all the doors belonging thereto be Nailed up, and securely fastned, except one, at which door, during such time before the intended Delivery, shall be set honest, impartial and responsible people, to see that no Child be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into the Room, and the Confederates say she was thereof deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> This would have rendred the design ineffectual: But by their surreptitious practices they frustrated all such endeavours which ('tis possible) Princess <hi>Ann</hi> would have pursued: And by violences and threats added to this surreptitiousness, they deterred those honest people from any such attempt or inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive observation, who perhaps had the conveniency and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to perform it.</p>
            <p>Again, The Trick of the labour and delivery was not so cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously done, nor indeed could the most dexterous actions have kept it from having been more plainly discovered, had good and impartial witnesses been present, who would have desired to see more than these witnesses did, as the Childs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of the Womb, a matter impossible to have been in any wise counterfeited; and who would, in case of a denial, have protested against their proceedings: But the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this imposture was owing to the weakness of the parties then present, who received whatever the Confederates impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and look'd no farther than what they were pleased to shew them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query,</hi> Whether every Soul in the Nation that but impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely believes the Queen had a seeming great Belly (for no one can prove it otherwise) that she said she had Milk, and was afraid of miscarrying, that she screamed, that a Child was taken out of the Bed, and an After-burthen shewn; whether I say, every one believing these things, cannot draw upon Oath as fair a deposition as any they have?</p>
            <p>From which it appears, that their preliminaries could be no other than pretensive, no free sight thereof being offered or allowed; and consequently the suspicions thence arising could not have been concealed by the greatest art or sophistry: And all were deterred from looking any farther into 'em, than what they were pleased to shew by threats of punity, which by only attempting, they must have been liable to, and yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not been suffered to see the truth of the thing designed. Those pitiful and little circumstances that fear, ignorance or design, made the Witnesses take on trust, were far from the plain, perfect and naked truth, which they might have seen, had honesty, courage or wisdom, but prevailed over their servile compliance.</p>
            <p>This falsly supplanting of an Heir is contrary to the Law of God and Man, that they were safe from the Judgmeuts of the first; their Priests by their Exorcisms bewitch them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the act was Meritorious; hereby giving the lye to the very nature within them. And when a man is drawn so far, he can with the greatest satisfaction imaginable, act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the known letter of the other, provided there is any prospect of the acts being kept private, or a hand that can protect him from the punity to be Incurred: So that privacy being the only thing desired, men of Riches, Authority, and ill Consciences, are those of all others, that can the most easily attain their desires: And consequently, the King as promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, can for his desired Interest effect it, whereby the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are rendred safe and unassailable.</p>
            <p>That design is highly capable of being performed, when besides the Wages it pays for the bringing it to pass, 'tis for the heavenly reward as well of the undertaker as promoter: When the promoter too can largely reward for their entring upon it, or punish, in case of refusal; and when once enter'd, their fear of being discovered to Justice, and the dread of As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sassination, by the Instigation of the powerful Parties imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, in case they wilfully detect the Cheat, or careless<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglect to perform what is requisite to a private perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will make them studiously endeavour that which may claim the highest rewards due from a Monarch, and what may secure their own Carcasses from the punishment, to which an open detection may render themselves obnoxious.</p>
            <p>There is yet a further advantage to such designs, when the Authors have such power as to make it Criminal, to look into their practices.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42098:4"/>
            <p>Rapes, Murders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where a publick acting would not only hinder the design, but deliver up the party to condign punishment, must be supposed to be more warily performed than actions of <hi>Petty Larceny,</hi> and therefore shall not be presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be, or possibly can be, subject to the like visible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, as things done in publick Streets and Places. Now if in these cases the Law accepts of matters only circumstantial, in evidence, how much more favourable ought it be to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances we bring, in as much as this case required more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy than the former; for in those, the violent passions of Lust and Revenge so hurry on the Actor, that they cannot be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to take due premeditation; and consequently, the Acts are more liable to be publickly seen. For the other cases, the Act may be performed notwithstanding an open detection, and their Lust and Revenge may be reach'd among thousands, but this is utterly lost, should it come but to the sight of any one party not of the confederacy. So that their steps in this design, being not incumbred with any passions, must be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to be done with the greater premeditation, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, a privacy unseen by any; to which privacy the Opulency and Authority of the Parties, as I said before, were much conducing, therefore this Cheat, above all others that have appeared to this day, ought to be admitted to be proved by Circumstances. Though I will <hi>ex alundante,</hi> lay down Facts sworn to by their Witnesses, and by the King owned to be true, <hi>viz.</hi> The whole Depositions, which by a due Genuine Construction, Learned Lawyers say, amount the greatest, nicest, and most strict Evidence, that the Law can require; both which I shall fully bring before you, only desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, e're I begin, the summing up the Evidence, to lay down the three following Observations.</p>
            <p>Let me remind you that the King slipp'd into the Throne, or at least had his Right of Succession, (which some of the long Robe say he had forfeited) continued to him by reason of our own unhappy Dissentions, I mean, that of Church-men and Presbyterians. And His Majesty being of neither, equally endeavoured the ruine of both, his Policy forced, and our Folly suffered our selves to be enjoyed by turns of all we could yield, the advantages he gained naturally flowing to strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hands of our own voracious Adversaries.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> seated him in the Throne of his Fathers, and the Presbyterians added Thunder to his Scepter, by their immoderate asserting some things they well-meaningly thought would be necessary, for the Establishing the Liberty they so earnestly wished for. And both gave him the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and convenience of raising an Army: The one by calling in <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and the other by suffering him to keep that Army in pay, when there was no good reason for its continuance.</p>
            <p>So then having brought him thus far, fortified with a very powerful Army, a mind thoughtful, severe, resolute, avenging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Prerogative stretcht to absolute Authority without reserve, directly leading to the greatest acts of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny when it had met with an opportunity, as it had with the depraved Will of one who would use it to the utmost. Add to this, as a driver on to execute such Resolves, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteracy, Heat and Malice of a Bigotted Queen, that Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously commanded him to do what the Villany of a Jesuit craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily insinuated, while another of the same Brood prepared the Kings Conscience to receive whatever they designed to stamp. The ill humours of which Body (I mean the Jesuits) were grown to a fermentation, their Mischiefs for some time had been kept in like the Quills of a Porcupine; who daring not, or having no opportunity to exert them, were grown the more in number to do larger Execution, and the longer, when dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, to enter the deeper.</p>
            <p>Consider the Advantages made by his unjustly assumed Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative and Army, &amp;c. under the Covert of which the Queen, Jesuits and Evil Counsellors commanded, connived at, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated to the greatest oppressions and slavery ever any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try lay under, whose Municipal Laws ordered Punishments for such Treasons, and to which the King himself is in some measure accountable; yet did they act with so much Violence as if we had been his Implacable Enemies, not his Loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but a conquered and forfeited Nation that had deserved no Quarter, but were designed for Slaughter, and our Bloods the Victim to appease their Rape and Revenge.</p>
            <p>This Hostile Invasion of our Liberties (but why should I use such a precarious term?) no, our Firth-rights, our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Inheritance as the Heirs of Gods Earth, was certain to be accounted for by the Successor apparent. Whereby all those Schools, Chapels and Convents, with such vast Charge Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently Erected, would have been sei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. They had run themselves into great Premunires, and laid out great Summs, and it was a sad Thought to call to mind the Punishment they had incurred for the one, and the loss to be sustained by the forfeiture of the other: That having designed for an everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power and inheritance, had no more than a small span be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themselves and the Gallows; no more than a short en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment during the life of an infirm King, and then to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up to the Justice of an abused Nation.</p>
            <p>This consideration made them seek for a prevention (of the punity supposed) by setting up a Popish Successor: Now if this consideration and way of prevention, were not first had e're they began their Oppressions, yet it naturally resolved it self (after perpetration) into the setting up such a one that might keep out the Heir, which would consequently have In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnified them from the punity incurred, and continued a lasting Enjoyment of their purchased Lands, by a further and better settlement of their Religion, than could be expected to be done in the Kings life time: Or had he lived till it had been done, it would have still been liable to be unravelled by a Protestant Heir; from all which they could in no wise be safe, but by trumping up a Suppositious Successor. This was their Hope, this was their Reprieve, this was their only Salvation; the Principles of their Religion first animated them to such Villanies, which necessitated them to this further act; this heaping ills upon ills, to cover themselves from Justice.</p>
            <p>Well then, notwithstanding the utter Impossibilities of the Queens bringing forth, yet a Child (and that a Male too) must be had, which being only pretensive and not real, must ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely be attended with apparent and bare-faced Rogueries, thinking (no question) by the strength they had gained, to uphold it, maugre all Suspicions and Discoveries, against our most Just, although Impotent Cries, which by their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions were so rendred, and had so continued, had not God raised up a Prince to deliver and protect us from the Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, acted under a pretended Successor, conceived in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, and upheld by the dint of a slavish and foolish Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Which I shall now proceed to detect.</p>
            <p>The Queens being with Child, was declared at a time before which they could not have set about such a thing, nor could they have possibly deferred it any longer; they could not do it till an Embassador had been at <hi>Rome,</hi> to settle a good Correspondence there, for his Majesty's being so much inclined to the <hi>French</hi> Interest, and not owning at that time, with the <hi>French</hi> King, the Popes Supremacy, therefore there was a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of settling that Affair, and to know whether his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness would stand by the pretended Prince, if the People of <hi>England</hi> should Dispute his Title, in case His Majesty could not decline the <hi>French</hi> Interest, nor at present submit to the Supremacy; which matters were all settled by the Earl of <hi>Castle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> so well, that about <hi>August</hi> following, came over a Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, of no less Quality than a Count, to finish this business, which no question was conceeded on all hands by His Majesty: For indeed, what terms could prevent the Pope from so blessed a Patrimony as <hi>England,</hi> or make the Zealous King to have the frown of His Holiness? And it cannot be supposed, altho' there had been no steps made towards such an Heir, but that the Nuncio would have urg'd it; for that the Popish Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were never known to slip any opportunity for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of their Cause, where either force, fraud, murder, war, or the greatest of Villanies, could gain any thing to it; and that there was such an opportunity is undeniable; and the King and Queen, if not first movers, yet were easily induced thereto. Now that they could not defer it longer, is likewise as evident, for that having lost their aim of that Slavish Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty they interded, and that it cooled every day more and more, this was to re-inforce the design; which that it might not quite dye, could not longer be deferred to quicken it. So that here is necessity, request, advice, propositions, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and interest, both for the Religion, the Inslaving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42098:4"/> the People, and his dear beloved Arbitrary Government.</p>
            <p>Because the most busie and designing of the Papists seemed so certain of a Child, maugre all the improbabilities alledged from the Weakness and Imperfections of the King and Queen; and so confident were they in the thing, that they confidently affirmed it should be a Boy, knowing that although the Queen could not have one, yet the Jesuits were about it, and would set up a Child, which being choice, and not chance, nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, would certainly be a Boy.</p>
            <p>And this matter of Fact is undeniable from what Mrs. <hi>Celier,</hi> in her printed Answer, to a certain Doctors Queries: Her Words are these, <hi>viz. And now Doctor, let me put you in mind, that tho' you have laughed at me, and some Doctors have accounted me a mad Woman these last four years, for saying her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty was full of Children, 'tis now proved so true, that I hope we shall have a Prince of</hi> Wales. Now here it can never be presumed that Mistress <hi>Celier</hi> knew it by her skill, for that all Doctors (with whom Mistress <hi>Celier</hi> is not to come in Competition for skill) thought it a thing so impossible that they laught at the assertion, which is the greatest gainsaying of a thing, insomuch as it was so plain, that they thought it neither required reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor demonstration. Well then, if these men by skill (for against that she excepts not) laught at it, what made Mistress <hi>Celier</hi> so arrogantly defend it, why truly for the reason above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, because she's a knowing discerning Woman, to whom the Jesuits will give or take advice, or communicate, as one the fittest in such tricks, so that she is cunning and arrogant we will readily acknowledge; the first is shown by slipping the Halter, which was her desert, for a Pillory; and the other, by this ridiculous and fanciful expression of the Queens being full of Children. In the same paragraph she intimated that the Queen should have all Boys, for she was full of 'um. Such things have often been attempted, and particularly in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reign, between which and this present, there certainly never was a fitter parallel: And ineeed Queen <hi>Mary</hi> went so well about it, that they could not take a better pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern (having it, no question, by tradition) for it went on so well till the pretended time of Delivery, that there was not the least hesitation, and had not then stopt, but that <hi>Philip</hi> would not acquiesce, in hopes that the Queen would dye, and then the Princess <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for all his Favours (this being one) would after such her Sisters Decease, reward him with her Person, which he pursued by going out of the Land to break his Queens heart, as it did, and then sollicited the thing after as is apparent; for he thought he might then raise the Spanish In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, and Popish Religion, as well from the Princess <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as before, and not let a Bastard and Impossor inherit both <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> part of his own Country) for there was no small hopes of the Princess <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> being then easie to be converted, so that it would have been <note place="margin">Baker'<hi>s Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, the Reign of Q.</hi> Mary.</note> much better for <hi>Philip</hi> could he have brought it about, for that the terms woud have been better on his part, by so much the more they had satisfaction of his Integrity, which before was untried and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known: All this meeting with a Beautiful Woman, and one apter for Children, was certainly the reason of his non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descension.</p>
            <p>But to the purpose; the reasons and necessity for such a Child at that time were these; there being no hopes of Queen <hi>mary</hi> to have Issue by reason of Infirmity, and lest dying, the Princess <hi>Elizabeth</hi> should have the Crown, which would, in all probability, have hurled down their re-edify'd <hi>Babel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the very same time Q. <hi>Mary</hi> declared herself quick, <hi>(viz.</hi> in <hi>November)</hi> so that her Conception, Quickning, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Delivery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were corresponding with ours; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Privy Council sent orders, with long preambles of Providence, care of Christs only Flock, throwing down of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Heresie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Bishops (as now) to make Prayers, Processions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heylin <hi>of the Reformation.</hi>
               </note> for the safe delivery of the Queen, and Indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the supposed Child; the Physicians, Ladies of Honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> justifie the Queens Conception, as to all signs, without so much as a doubt, or may-be of a Tympany. And farther, gave <note place="margin">Foxes <hi>Acts and Monuments.</hi>
               </note> out her reckoning to be out at <hi>June,</hi> against which time, Rockers, Midwifes, Nurses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (but here ours out-did them) were provided: And what too was the most like this (then as now) none during such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended bigness, was admitted, on behalf of the Lady <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> to view her Breasts or Belly, (but as now) several were discarded and disfavourited for putting forth broad Speeches of their doubtings. Nay, there was a general and open suspici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as now) on the <hi>Protestant,</hi> and as great a pretended cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty on the <hi>Papist</hi> party; so that we see the <hi>Protestants</hi> may be (now as then) in the right, and the <hi>Papists</hi> in the wrong.</p>
            <p>Nay, the necessity of the Papists are greater now than then, therefore argues the more zealousness for it on that side; the Papists at that time were more in number, by which a depres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of their Religion being establisht, would be harder to be done either by Parliament or Convocation: The Papists then had not been so obnoxious to the Laws, and so might expect better treatment than now from the next Successor.</p>
            <p>They hoped likewise that the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> might have succeeded, so needed not such bars as now.</p>
            <p>And should the <hi>Protestants</hi> have prevailed in a Successor, there was no fear of any trouble it could cause to other <hi>Popish</hi> Countrys, as now in the case of <hi>France,</hi> for then the <hi>Protestants</hi> were weak, the dissertion of the <hi>Hollander</hi> then not thought of.</p>
            <p>Nor should we wonder at this going on so, when that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Parliament, composed of above 500 the most wise in the Nation, who not only upheld the report, but enter'd into the consideration of provisions for the Child, and the Queen, with all the zeal imaginable. So that as certain that they, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Parliament would not have so acted, had they had any suspicion; so certain it is that they did such things because they had none. Therefore if such a body was deceived, much more might they expect we should singly, there being no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention since for Wisdom and Authority to look into it; and it is but an idle quibble to cry how can so many Great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages, Privy Councellours, Ladies of Quality, Peeresles, Physicians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be deceived, when they have taken their Oaths for that, this Parliaments free Action and Impartiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was acted on as great circumstances as these on Oath can pretend to, and yet those circumstances were all false and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensive. Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Case was harder to play than this, for they were obliged to keep it known <note place="margin">Heywoods <hi>Troubles of Q.</hi> Elizabeth.</note> from K. <hi>Philip,</hi> whereas here was no need of that, for our King assisted in it; and as K. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> dissent was the only thing confounded it at the upshot, so our Plot had that very assent they only wanted; our present King not only forwarded it all along, but at the pinch was more busie and industrious than the rest. So that if that wanted one stone to finish, this had it and did compleat it.</p>
            <p>And as there was Bonfires, Entertainments, Feasts, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessions, <hi>Te Deums, &amp;c.</hi> beyond Sea now, so was there then; for a rumour being spread that she was delivered, all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and <hi>Europe</hi> rejoyced publickly; and pray what greater testimony of a Birth than hearsay had those in our days for a rejoycing: So that it was not the real circumstances of that as well as this that caused these actions, but lies and hearsays.</p>
            <p>Nay, after all it fared just as now with ours, for none of that Cabal ever on their Death-beds, or otherwise declared the Intrigue; by whar means they raised her Belly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and carried it on; so that its not being found out is no argument against it, for that that was on all hands allowed to be a cheat, and yet the particulars never came to light, but stands just as this does; <hi>Ergo,</hi> this is a Cheat, notwithstanding the impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, or rather impossibility of its ever coming to light; tho indeed there was some difference, for there was no occasion after Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s death to look after that, as there is now into this; lest the King keeps him beyond Sea, and may marry him to some Potentates Daughter, who themselves or Issue perhaps 100 years hence, when they have strength to harm us, may trump up this Title, which tho perhaps may never be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced, nor a Conquest thereon gained, yet we know such cases often occasion great troubles, and effusion of Blood; and a war may be brought into our own Land, for tho the power may now be weak (as who but a petty Head will Affiance a pretended Prince) yet may in years to come much annoy us; for what expectance could there be of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness 200 years since? But what is the misery of all, the Queen remaining obstinate, may, in case the Child should dye in a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42098:5"/> Foreign Lrnd, amongst her own Creatures, taking the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Indistinction of such young Children, may, I say, get another in its room, to uphold the same Implacable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions.</p>
            <p>Note, that about the time the Conception was pretended, Father <hi>Peters</hi> was made a Privy-Counsellour; and as he was one of the managers at first, so now he was to carry on the report, by giving it there all the favour imaginable; to see that it was not contested, and if it were, to satisfie their doubts, to stir up the Lords to make Orders concerning the Queen and Child, (which had not been so proper from the King, nor could it have been put into <hi>Arundel</hi>'s, or the rest of the <hi>Popish</hi> Lords mouths, who knew not so well as <hi>Peters</hi> what to insist on,) and generally to make a voice, and use perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in all things that might conduce to the favour of the Cheat, the Queen, and Child; and fixing them in the certainty of her bigness, that so they might diffuse it abroad, on the words of Privy Councellors.</p>
            <p>But as a <hi>Preludium</hi> to this, I cannot but take notice of the Processions, Pilgrimages, Offerings to <hi>Loretto,</hi> Washings at St. <hi>Winifreds,</hi> recourse to salubrious Waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and it was ever observable in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that when any grand Villany was design'd, there has been always such fopperies, ever more than what was usual at other times, and being so done, some great design ever hapned afterwards. Now if in the whole series of her life the Queen hath never done such things before, tho the like necessity, time and opportunity; it is to be asked for what reason she went about um now? why not 8 or 9 years ago, or when she first came to the Crown.</p>
            <p>The impossibility of the Queens being with Child appears from the Infirmity of the Male agent, the Disease supposed, having a Natural Designation against the Generative faculties, as matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for all the parts, as they are then most imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately weakened, so they have the least power to perform their natural functions.</p>
            <p>The abovesaid is yet more corroborated, his not having for these many years past any by his Misses, who are more apt than the Queen, and with whom 'tis more probable he has a greater gust: Yet perhaps it will be urged, that he has had Children and healthy, since that time, by such Women, and has likewise had some by his Queen, tho weak and infirm: To this I answer, That the reason of his having those, and healthy too, by his Women, was effected by the sound apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of their Constitution, which made up what the King want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Queen, as I shall shew hereafter, was utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to do this, for that she was of a very ill habit of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as well as the King, and the Children born of them were ever weak, for indeed, 'twas impossible they should be other, but this Child is of a very good Constitution; <hi>Ergo</hi> it is none of their Natural Issue.</p>
            <p>Now if any shall on the Kings having sound Children by sound Women fifteen years ago, ask why he may not now? First, it is not by those Women, and secondly, it cannot be any certainty they were of his Getting, but of some other mens; for one that is Mercenary to the King only for money, and not love, will, for love or money, lye with any one else: For indeed, how can he be certainly said to be Father to a Child whose Mother several have Bedded, for they always lay the Child to those best can keep it; Pride makes them do it, to have their Off-spring Lords and Ladies. So that if they had other Paramours they were probably more healthy, and being more healthy, the Conceptions might be more probably from their Seed.</p>
            <p>Although it should be conceeded the King was apt, yet I may say, it is improbable for the Queen to have a Child by the King; nay, that it is utterly impossible, and as there are degrees of probability, this must be owned to be of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, since an intermission within the age of Child-bearing, the Husband being with her, does argue an impediment; and therefore she cannot be allowed to be as apt as a Woman teem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yearly; therefore she having an impediment, it is more improbable she should have Children than another woman.</p>
            <p>Some of the <hi>Popish Party</hi> when they are drove to acknowledge the incapacity of the King, tell a blasphemous and wicked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention (if true) that the Holy Ghost was to appear to her and make her Conceive, when she put on the pretended Smock of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which Apparition, they say, was in the likeness of the Pope's Nuntio, and so by an <hi>Inuendo</hi> give us to understand that he got it on the Queen, the known strength of his Body making amends for all the failures of the King and Queen; knowing, that the Laws of the Land allow all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren born in Wedlock, the Husband not out of the Land, though never so many obvious Reasons gain-say: These People desiring an Heir, tho' with the shame and infamy of the French <hi>Lewis,</hi> between his Mother and a Cardinal.</p>
            <p>Others that will not allow of this, say, the Queen is Chast, and would not do such a thing; if she is Chast, the Kings Incapacity, and her apparent Weakness, can not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Child; if she is not Chast, and that it was by some other and not he, it is altogether as impossible, for that no means on Earth can possibly make her bring forth so lusty a Child; nor if it were possible can we own an Heir so gotten; therefore their own Argument shuts them out from havin gone this way: And for the reason above-said, concerning the Kings Incapacity, I appeal to their own Conscience if they think it not impossible.</p>
            <p>But here will be urged the Childs Indispositions at <hi>Richmond,</hi> therefore it being weak it is more likely it was the King and Queens. To this I answer, that such Indispositions arose not from the weakness of the Parents, but from Wind, want of the Dug, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> incident to the best Constitutions of Child and Parents; and therefore I again urge, that had it been possible for her to have brought forth (which none can grant) it must have been weak, puny and Imperfect, as Children are when of weak Parents; but this is neither puny nor imperfect: As such therefore it was not brought forth by the Queen, or got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the King.</p>
            <p>As the Physicians laught at her being with Child, so did the King, being forced to own for Modesties sake, by reason of the known Infirmities of both, that it was (as he was heard to express himself) a very odd thing; which is a sort of an expression for all things being incredible, unusal and impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Great Circumstance of the King and Queens weaknesses, and incapacities, appear from the Considerations of those three Children formerly had; the first a Boy, weak, and short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived; the second was a Boy too, but weaker, and shorter lived than the first; so their Capacities declining more and more, at last it dwindled to a puny Girl, and the next time of her usual Conception none at all; so by consequence growing every year weaker and weaker, and more incapable, their faculties must in ten years intermission be uncapable of Generation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the help of Art or Nature.</p>
            <p>'Tis again urged that she fainted, and sweat ran down her forehead; and it was observable, that these Indispositions were always in publick, when great concourses of <hi>Protestants</hi> were present; what can this argue to a real Child-bearing, when pride will oblige Ladies for the love of a small wast, to lace themselves so hard, that such things are very usual with 'um. The Ladies undergoing such pain, was only the pleasure of Pride, and certainly the Queens pleasure in doing it was greater, because it answered her necessities of a seeming Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, for what is such a forc'd pain, in the case where Life it self is scarcely valued, so it might have produced but a Child, to be received as Heir Apparent.</p>
            <p>And what is Corroborating to this, the case she found was always by loosening her Garments; certainly, the straitness of which, had only caused these pretended Child-bearing Symptoms.</p>
            <p>The Circumference of her Belly was neither large enough for a Child so lusty, nor naturally like other Womens; (I must confess I cannot in this point express my self, but that it was not like other Womens being really with Child, all must know that have more skill than I) the reason of the first is, because a little made Belly is easier to conceal than an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary great one; and for the fashioning of it, they did no question their best, which best did not reach a reality, or true similitude of a real burden; I could not inquire after these things lest I should be suspected, for having some more design than every body else, by which the Author hereof might be found.</p>
            <p>Methought she did not bend in the back, nor had she the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42098:5"/> extension and protension of the hips, as in another Lady then standing by her, whom I had no doubt to believe was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise. Tall women commonly bend most in the back, which being most perceptible, in them, like them she strove to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick it, but it was not like a real bigness, which was more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, by the formality and stiffness of her Legs, Neck, Head and Mouth: for that when she seemed most to bend, her Neck seemed stiff, and her Speech was hesitated, gross and drawling, like those that speak in the Throat.</p>
            <p>But suppose her Bigness appeared to be exactly proportioned, yet cannot any certainty be from that deduced; because no question Queen <hi>Mary</hi> had a bigness which seemed very real, or else it cannot be supposed the then Parliament and Privy Council would have done so much concerning it, whom we cannot in Justice think were partial, but from their pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, so well was the Cheat handled during her pretended bigness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aristophanes</hi> tells us of a woman so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedly brought to bed; therefore long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <note place="margin">Aristophanes in his Themophoriasonsai.</note> faintings, bellys, and all other things may be done, so as not only to deceive all, but likewise the Husband, were he not consenting, (as in the Case he relates) what then may be done by a Husband, a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful party of Nurses, Ladies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in fine a whole Court, who having been obnoxious, helpt on the Cheat for self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation.</p>
            <p>From the parties immediately imploy'd, as Mrs. <hi>Wilks, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labadie, Turini, &amp;c.</hi> busie, rigid, bigotted, villanous people, having the Cunning and the Conscience for such a wickedness; so that when people the most fit for such a purpose are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the very uses tis known they are of all people the most fit for, this, I say, argues the necessity they had for such sort of people, without whom they could not have done it; for if I'le have a Murther done, I must not seek for the most Conscientious, but Rogues, Bandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s and Padders; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign being judged always by the parties.</p>
            <p>From her pretended likelihood of miscarrying, which is so easie a thing to pretend, it relying wholly on her own word, and we know there must be great pretences, where there's no reality to uphold the end designed: Indeed had she miscarried it had been a sign she had been with Child then, but no proof of this pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> birth now; so that in reality she was not in a capacity to miscarry, nor was it convenient to say she had; as to the first, not being with Child, 'twas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible she should miscarry; and as she was not but pretended, 'twould have hindred the thing designed; and that if she had said she miscarry'd, and had began again, such pretended mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage would only have been thought that they could not have accomplished their business this time, and that they must begin some other time; and the rather, for that the Queen could not have produced any good witness to say they saw the <hi>Fetus</hi> come out, for that it never was in; and I hope if such a thing had been pretended, and no more proof appeared thereof than now of the delivery, we may in all Justice conclude it a cheat, a pretence, and forgery; only necessary amusements, like a Jugglers flourishing his Stick, with a <hi>Hictius Doctius;</hi> for it is very consistent with pretended bignesses, to say they had like to miscarry, and yet say they did not.</p>
            <p>From the Kings going to <hi>Chattham</hi> just before this pretended likelihood of miscarriage, for no real occasion known, but the private one of designing, to have her pretend a Miscarriage, and so send for him, that his riding all Night back again, and seeming troubled, thereby to amuse the people, that they might think by this his seeming trouble, that the Queen was really with Child, or if it was a Cheat, that he was not in it; wherers it was the Part he was to Act.</p>
            <p>From the thing that was pretended to make this fright, which was a meer designed lye, for one of her Maids brought word, the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> her Brother, was Dead, which perhaps might be Madam <hi>Turini,</hi>
               <note place="margin">News Letters.</note> who with the King and Queen, had pack'd up this, to make the pretended reason of her fright feazible; and indeed, though there was the least occasion imaginable to think it (for neither the Embassador who first 'tis likely should know, heard any thing of it, nor was it ever known that any brought such word from <hi>Italy)</hi> yet it was the properest thing in the World to lay the lye so far off, that the reasons of the unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness of the thing might not be discovered, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how it came about scanned. 'Twas the pretended death of one, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Kings, was the most likely to fright her, and why it was not the Kings, was because there was no grounds for such report, and the falsity of the thing would have been quickly seen through, being so near at home, and might have led us to the Design. But suppose the Embassadour had declared it, and that the Duke was seemingly ill, the Embassadour was a Creature, and so was his Master, who could easily Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to bring such a rumour about. Nay, supposing it was not Madam <hi>Turini, Powis,</hi> nor none of the Confederates, yet it might be first Canted about by them, and so come through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hands at last to the Queen, by a Protestant unconcerned in the Design; just as Rogues drop feigned Letters, that they may gain Credit from the reputation of him that takes 'um up, who cannot be suspected, for had the Rogue himself been seen to do it, we could suspect nothing but Roguery.</p>
            <p>That her only saying she had Milk, and not shewing it, is the most notorious sign of its being all a Cheat imaginable, for that it is agreeable to a Cheat, to say they have that which they have not. As suppose a man is Condemned to be hang'd, he Pleads his Pardon, they desire to see it, he says he hath it about him, but will neither shew it himself, nor will let others search, and will rather be condemned and hanged than shew it, shall it not therefore be presum'd he's a Lyer; for would not he, if he had it, produce it to save his Life? Were such things suffered, it were the very nearest way to have none hanged at all, since all would plead such a Pardon, and the price of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Necks would only be to say, I have such a thing, which in truth I have not. So in the Queens Case, shall it ever be presum'd she had Milk, only because she said so, and never condescended to shew it; can her Word only in this case, be any more valued than such a Criminals: Had she not by shewing this Milk, saved the Crown, its Rights, and all to the Child? And can it ever be thought she would lose those Rights belonging to her Son, rather than give such easie Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as might have been the great means of securing him in 'um, had it not only saved the Rights to her Child, but took off the Calumnies laid against her? Certainly, if one may be supposed, in such a case, to have Milk because ones self says so, and consequently to have a Child in the Belly, 'tis one of the easiest things in the World to pervert, and put by all right most births can pretend to.</p>
            <p>Therefore the premises are conclusive of this point, that it was only a pretence, and could not shew it because she had it not.</p>
            <p>Had there been Milk, Interest so obliged her to discover it, that certainly her Cloaths would have been turned down to all persons, it being the greatest pleasure imaginable to take off abuses when wronged, all persons of different principles being willing to expose the Lyes and Forgeries of the other, and the Queen being so used, would certainly have defended her self, Husband, and Parties Honesty, which to do, would not only have been pleasure and satisfaction, but the greatest advantage of worldly Interest to her self, Husband, and Religion she is so zealous to restore.</p>
            <p>Besides, if she had Milk before the Birth, 'tis unusual; if after, there is neither pretence, proof, nor hear-say, although the Nation was more dissatisfied after the Delivery than before. Indeed, had the Birth been so, as to evince all suspicion, then it had been needless to speak of the Milk, but when the sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion continued, not to take off that which you desired might cease, when you pretend you have that that would do it, was certainly because you had not really what you pretended; did you desire the suspicion should continue, or desire it to cease? If to continue, it is utterly Absurd, if to cease, why did you not use the means, since the deferring it brought on a farther Infamy?</p>
            <p>The having Milk being almost as satisfactory as the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, why was not the Princess <hi>Ann</hi> shewed it before she went to the <hi>Bath;</hi> since the Queen knew not whether the Princess might ever return again, (as in the case of death,) the Queen might be suddenly brought to bed e're she could come: If the Milk had been shown to the Princess <hi>Ann,</hi> her Death-bed Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had made much for the Childs Title, as far as the certainty of the Queens really having Milk would go. And tho the Princess
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42098:6"/> had missed (as she did) of being there, the certainty of the Queens having Milk was a great sign she had been pregnant, and therefore 'twas more probable that this was the Child of her Body, than when any pretends to have Milk and will not shew it, (tho the Interest was to herself and not Princess <hi>Ann)</hi> nor acquit herself of the slander she desires to be acquitted of; which remaining, would redound much to her dishonour and prejudice.</p>
            <p>Indeed some Bigotted Papists talk of Milk, and seeing Milk; and no body in such cases should offer to speak unless they saw the Milk, and were satisfied, and could give as good reasons for such satisfaction as can reasonably be desired; but instead thereof they prate so foolishly intricate, especially about the Milk, not one of them giving so much as a pertinent, or plainly demonstrated reason of this question of seeing the Milk drop out; but on the contrary shew that they nor any else did see the Milk, in a way that any man can be concluded, by their expressing themselves not to except against the falsity; but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the genuine sense of their words, and that they did see the matters they pretend to have seen, yet I say all their tattle is of no validity, (as seeing her Smock wet and so forth) but when they come to be grafpt and considered, are no manner of satisfaction, as shall be shewn in my Examen of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions.</p>
            <p>No Woman ever draw'd, no Doctor or other ever saw her Breast, or considered on her Milk, nor were any things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by the Doctors concerning her Breast, which to be sure was omitted, lest on the Queens saying she wanted some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for her Breasts, which were in a bad state, the Doctors should desire to see 'um ere they prescribed.</p>
            <p>If they desired either to satisfie the world that she had Milk, knowing the World excepted against it, or desired a Child, and were minded the Child should thrive and live, she ought to have kept her Milk running (if she had it) after the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to answer the Exceptions, and as the Childs Life was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps desired as much as any Childs ever in the World, they ought to have taken care to preserve and bring it up, by a way the most certain so to do, which was to let it suck.</p>
            <p>If it shall be answered, that the Queen had no Milk after the Delivery, (if really with Child) I offer that 'tis false, and inconsistent; for that lean Women have it most, and if they have Milk before Delivery, 'tis a sign they have it plentifully afterwards; if she had it not plentifully after, because she had is not before, then all the pretences of having it before fall, and shew there is a design, where some pretend to have that which they have not.</p>
            <p>If it shall be objected, that she would not suckle it because of the trouble, 'tis very inconsistent with the great desire she had for a Child, that she should boggle at so small a trouble, to continue it alive, when, could it be admitted Heir, as then they expected, she would have laid down her life.</p>
            <p>It cannot be excused by saying the Queen was weak, for neither any apparent sign of weakness was on her after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Delivery, nor was it indeed possible she should be weak after such easie Labour, not having since gotten Cold, as was known or ever heard of.</p>
            <p>There always is some apparent Reason and great Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had, whether a Child shall be brought up by hand or no, it being an unnatural way, and cannot but on great circumstances be done. But of any Circumstances, or reasons for so doing in this case, besides what I have before alledged, no man can find the most weak or sophistical pretence.</p>
            <p>That altho it was for the Queens own Interest, her Childs, the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Religion throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> and every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual professor thereof, to shew her Breasts, not only for the reality of Milk being there, but that skilful Women might be satisfied whether there was any Conception or real bigness, by the fashion of the Duggs, which the Princess of <hi>Denmark,</hi> or some Deputed (as I am credibly inform'd) desired to see; the refusal of which, cannot be rendred otherwise than that the Queen would have thereby been betray'd, had she offered her Breasts to inspection; and as I have urged Interest all along for her sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wing them, had she been with Child; so Interest is such a true test of most matters, that she here does stick to it, and out of Interest will not shew 'um, because the Cheat might go on.</p>
            <p>Well then, the whole business of the Milk stands thus: It is by them pretended, that about two and twenty Weeks after Conception, she had Milk, which by the way is very unusual; yet in all that time, did ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> any pretend that they saw it? 'Twas never drawn by any Woman, young Puppy, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; no Medicaments were used about it, either before or after the pretended Delivery; nor did any Protestant (though requiring so to do) or other conscientious body ever see it, nor was Milk shewn to any Papist or other, so that there can be any certainty inferred that such Milk was the Queens, nor was this Milk, (which is implyed to be of Quantity by her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a lean Woman, and that she had much before the birth, and so consequently had much after) ever given to the Child; nor was it offer'd the Nipple, to try whether it would take it, though so proper for its Nourishment; it was never dryed, either by any natural cause, nor by any medicament prescribed or made, on the Doctors, or any else Inspection thereof; it came, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and went away none seeing it, or using means to dry it up. And the Child was brought up by hand, without the Doctors, or any others advice on the Milk that was bad, which ought always to be considered in the giving, or not giving it, altho' the Child apparently wanted the Nipple, and was much Indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed for the not having it. All these are such evident marks of only pretensive Milk, that no excuse can be offered in Palliation.</p>
            <p>The same Circumstances of an Imposture, may be offered concerning her Belly, which was never shewn to, nor suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be felt by any Protestant Lady; nor was there any thing done to take off the Suspicion from the People, and the great Scandal on her self, which no body can say she desired, for that she and the King might have dyed, before they could have clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Arguments, of which this Counterfeit Belly was one; and can it be thought that she purposely desired to leave her Child in the Trouble and Confusion of an obscure Title? Can it be thought she loved Scandal and Reproach? If not, and pleaded her Innocency, why did she not demonstrate it? For when a business is in suspence between parties, and the one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends he can shew that which will confute the other, and doth not shew it, tho oblig'd thereto by Self-interest, and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment still of being thought an Imposture worse than before, such a step (I say) only of pretensions, and no proof, is the greatest of Evidence against them, when they were thereto required, to see her Belly, which no question she would have done, not only to such particular parties, but to all modest and creditable Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; there not only being a sort of pleasure in proving ones self innocent, and in this case the greatest gain on the one hand, but a disappointment on the other, were not the scandal taken off; so that all might be satisfied it was the right Heir, which without good and plain satisfaction, none can expect we should admit of.</p>
            <p>For that her Nurse, Mrs. <hi>Delabadie,</hi> was, as I hear, one who had never been about her before; one of whose skill she was not assured; and therefore to commit herself and Child wholly to the management of a sly, bigotted, ill-reputed Woman, shews that she had not so much need of Skill as Roguery: Now altho she was of such a Character, and the Queen had known her before, some plausible pretence might have been made, (as the Queens trying her skill and care,) but to pick such a party out, in pursuance of the Cheat they were charged with to be about, and which slander could have no better been taken off, than by imploying for her Nurses honestly reputed Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whose testimony would have more been believed in behalf of the Childs Title: None but an ill Woman is either fit to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, or will uphold Roguery by Oaths; but this is an ill Woman, <hi>Ergo</hi> she was fittest for Roguery, and her Oath not to be relyed on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query,</hi> whether the Queen never had more than one Nurse? Or if an ordinary Citizens Wife is not usually better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided?</p>
            <p>Because there was no more Nurses provided than Mrs. <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badie,</hi> a thing never known, but very agreeable to a private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign; for this design was only to be trusted to few, (the only danger was of having many concern'd, which was absolutely necessary to be avoided) for Nurses, as 'tis usual, and especially in a Queens case, are about the Child-bearing Woman long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand, and so could not be kept from seeing those things all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42098:6"/> the time of bigness, and at the time of delivery, which in this design were not fit to be trusted to 'um, it being the hardest thing to manage a Cheat by numbers, so as to keep it for ever secret; whereas a Juggle between two may be kept in 1000 ways, two are poisoned soonest, two by natural Lives may be sooner in their Graves than four; there's a hundred such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies in a small number, which cannot be kept private by many.</p>
            <p>But here it will be objected, if a great many Nurses are less suspicious, then the Queen might have had 'um, and not call'd 'um till all had been over: To which I reply first, If they had been hired, and not imployed before or at the delivery, to what purpose were they hired, and sure people being hired and not employed, but designedly kept out of the way, whereby they may not see that which must only take off the suspicion, would have made the suspicion much more: But secondly, the Nurses so hired, and not being suffered to be about the Queen during her bigness, nor near the Chamber at her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as is usual, would have made them greatly suspect foul play, which being known and witnessed by them, would make much against 'um; nay, had they been never so little time before (about her) though the Queens Instruments designed to decoy them away at the Labour, in that time, I say, they must have seen the forgery of her Belly, which they being numbers, could not have concealed; and such an Item by the Queens Nurses, had made folks been more bold to watch their waters, at the Delivery, in as much as this could give them the more certainty to their designed looking after it; as this did of Mrs. <hi>Delabadies</hi> being away so near the Labour, (which was necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry too, as I shall shew in her Deposition, notwithstanding her being a party.)</p>
            <p>Query, Whether she did not use to provide a Wet Nurse, at her other Deliveries: And whether all persons of Quality, though they resolved to give Suck themselves, do, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing such resolution, provide a Wet Nurse, lest the Child would not take the Breast, or that such Mother may be Ill, or have a sore Breast.</p>
            <p>There were no Men Midwifes ordered to be ready to attend the Queen, if occasion should be, which though she might not have necessity for, yet they are often used; and sure a Queen ought to have as great a preparation of what is within a possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of being wanted, as of what certainly will be; but the reason was, lest they should visit the Queen before the Labour, and so discover the proportions of her Belly, or be near Court, and at the noise of the Labour come to it, who could not be so easily cheated as other men, nay, as Women, for being Doctors, they could have distinguished the very Cries, whether true or Counterfeit.</p>
            <p>Query, whether she did not use, at her three former Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to have such men in readiness? whether others of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty do not the like? and whether it is not very convenient for all Women, but more especially, for the help of a Queen, and welfare of an Empires Heir so much by the Parents desired?</p>
            <p>Her Doctors of Physick were not order'd to attend against the second reckoning; and this was omitted, lest they should be so diligent as to follow the Court, and be too near about her, they lived so far off, that of four or five, but one, was so near as to be there till after the pretended Delivery.</p>
            <p>And though their Majesties respective Doctors have Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, appointed about their Lodgings, at all their Courts, and at all times, whether occasion or none, and do attend such Chambers; yet was this so carried on, that her Doctors attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, as usually at such Chambers, though the occasion was so great.</p>
            <p>Nor in fine, was there any one more about her, or concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than Mrs. <hi>Delabadie</hi> and <hi>Wilkes;</hi> nor did the Midwife Lodge at Court as is usual, and had been proper, considering there was but she and another provided for the Queen, one being away on no pretended reason, and the other on a pretence of illness; the reasons of which designed absence, I shall consider in my Examen of Mrs. <hi>Delabadies</hi> Deposition.</p>
            <p>The Queen ought by the very obligations of her own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, that no objection might have been against the birth, to have given notice of the House and Room she intended to lie in, that the Princess, or any for her, might have search'd such Room, and be satisfied there was no false doors, traps, or other conveniences for Juggling; or if there were, to nail them up; which is not a whimsey and expediment of my own, but a written Law, and Edict founded on great Reason and Justice, and which being the Law of Reason, ought to have been done here, (it being allowed of in such cases for a most convenient direction;) as nailing up such doors, and suspicious places, not suffering any more than one door (whereas here was three or four) to keep a guard at that door, for so many days before the delivery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but instead of this, the house was designed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conccaled till within a few hours of her coming; the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess 100 miles off, self-interest obliged the Queen to do this on their parts; and if the Princess had not sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cht nor nail'd up the doors, it had been to her own peril and the Childs Title ne're the obscurer; and such a Test all true Births will bear, but this would not.</p>
            <p>There was so much stress laid on this Law, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Heir had before searcht such womans Belly, (which was so far from being askt to be done by the Queen, that she denied it; altho it was her own Interest to desire others to view it.) I say, though the Heir had before searcht her Belly, and was satisfied of her being pregnant, yet the Law and Reason provided this, after Circumspection, lest bringing a Dead Child, she should change it for a Living; or, being a living Girl, might be changed for a Boy. Nay, the Law ordered that the Heir, or those by him deputed, might keep her from going, and not suffer her to go out of their sights, for so many days before the expected Delivery, and to search all that should come near her, during that time, or at the Labour.</p>
            <p>Now these Orders being made, and obliging people to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, not only for the Interest and Reason, but for the Penalty, forcing all, that were pregnant of that, which might displant another, to use the Orders, or else to be supposed an Imposture, taking it for granted, that if such Orders were not used, there was, and might be Cheating, but if used, it was presumed they could not do it; there being in that Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, all that the Wit of Man can devise against it. But these things were neither followed, nor was there an innocent negligence, but a combined endeavour to prevent any insight, as Law, Reason, and their own Interest required.</p>
            <p>Now if the Law cannot presume there was an Heir truly born, unless such directions were followed, much less shall this be presumed which wilfully omitted them; but it had not the usual, plain, and simple Circumstances, attending the most common births, where no Rights is contested, but instead thereof, a whole train of pretences and inconsistences.</p>
            <p>So that resolving not let any know where she intended to lie in, sometimes it was given out she intended for <hi>Windsor,</hi> anon St. <hi>James</hi>'s, then <hi>Richmond,</hi> and <note place="margin">News Letters.</note> next day <hi>Windsor</hi> again, lest people very curious, or imployed, should plant themselves in some apartment to observe, and no question but some did design it, both for their own satisfaction, and an expected reward, could they discover any thing; for as there must be a great many steps to such a Cheat, such steps must needs have been discried by persons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently and privately placed about the Court, in or near the very Chamber she intended to be in, or if they could not plant themselves there unseen, yet to observe by frequently being about those Lodgings, which might have been well performed by any belonging to the Houshold or Bed-chamber, which certainly some honest body design'd, but were by the various reports prevented.</p>
            <p>And here perhaps it may be objected, that the time from setting up the Bed was sufficient for making approaches to observe: To this I offer, that tho such parties might move by the principles of mistrust, yet they ne're thought she would have done so contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all likelihood of the thing she was to pretend; a whole month before her reckoning! a Bed set up but one day! and she at the place not twelve hours, with nothing provided! not so much as Linne, Nurse, nor Midwife about her; it not being twelve hours, and that in the time of rest, between which and eight the next morning it could not be known she was gone there; and after that there was so little time to plant, observe, or consider how to make approaches, that it was altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible. Besides, that their business was so laid, that before her being in or near her Labour, the Child was brought into
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42098:7"/> the very Bed, no body but <hi>S—d</hi> present, so that none could have done any thing towards the discovery, for who thought at eight her labour would begin at half an hour after, especially those who had not yet heard such pretended labour: And had this been a true delivery, it is very in probable she would have lain in at St. <hi>James,</hi> because all her other Children born there dyed; which Women (being commonly superstitious) would have taken from the fatality of the place; so as <hi>Windsor</hi> was the most convenient had it been a true birth, but the most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient for an imposture; and <hi>St. James</hi> was the most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient for the first, but the most convenient perhaps of any Court in the whole World, by reason of the adjoyning Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents scituation, for the other.</p>
            <p>The going to the place of her lying in, being the alarm for all concerned to gather about, had she given such a long notice as her going from hence to <hi>Windsor,</hi> which consequently must have done her harm, inasmuch as it was their Interest to keep those approaches to her delivery as close as possible; and indeed this was the only course, for the Park-gates being lockt and all quiet, 'twas no more than coming down the stairs from the Gallery, cross a Garden as it were to another apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the same Court, and the alarm they so much dreaded never started.</p>
            <p>So that it being necessary for the Queen not to go from <hi>White-Hall</hi> to St. <hi>James</hi>'s till a few hours before, had it been at any other Court further off, the notice of the right Womans being in Labour, could not conveniently have been brought to the Queen, and the Queen to run there soon enough to have the Child seem new born; but here the Queen might have word brought of the Labour, slip away, and catch it reeking warm from the Womb, and so no time lost about keeping the Child quiet by its navel-string.</p>
            <p>And it was not convenient for the Queen to lie in at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> because a Woman could not possibly have been privately Delivered there, by reason of the multitude and concourse of people, in all the rooms, through which the Child must have been brought to the Queens Chamber.</p>
            <p>But at St. <hi>James</hi>'s there was a Convent adjoyning, where a Woman might be kept all the time of her bigness, or come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it any evening and none perceive, as is evident from its scitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; here a Woman might cry out as loud as she would in Labour, and have all the help from this very Mrs. <hi>Wilks</hi> and <hi>Delabadie,</hi> who might likewise be concealed, it being a large place within Walls and Cloysters, out of all hearing, or any intercourse of people to disturb them.</p>
            <p>And as this Convent was certainly a most convenient and private place for the true Mothers Delivery, so I appeal to all persons that know the Rooms, Stairs and Passages, belonging to the Convent and Palace, whether there are not two several direct and commodious ways, whereby the Child so Born, may be privately conveyed from the said Convent (it not being above three Rods) to the Queens Bed-chamber: These ways or passages, are so plain, so direct, and without the least In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacies or Windings, that the most hardned cannot deny or except against, on the least pretence of publickness or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, but as if they had been made on purpose. And which is evidently demonstrated by a Map or Survey of the Convent and Palace annexed to the Book, for the satisfaction of those who have not the opportunity to go to <hi>St. James</hi>'s to view the premises.</p>
            <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> delivers▪ so there is as convenient a conveyance for the Child after i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the great Bed-chamber and other Rooms thereunto belonging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> joyn to the Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, are near the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chappel and Rooms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be back of the Chamber where the Queens pretended labour was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> belonging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Queens Chamber and the Dormitories▪ which Chambers, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might be cleared, the King went to his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in or near such Chambers▪</p>
            <p>And it must be supposed that there was several Women with Child at the same time, looking within few days of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; so that had the Queen spoke of her own pretended reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning, corresponding to the first Womans reckoning, and at the upshot it had proved a Girl, they must have stayed for the next, and the Ladies, Princess, and Nobility would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained about her, notwithstanding she came not just then, and would not have gone away; so that tho the next might be a Boy, yet she could not so well bring her matters about, they being in the way.</p>
            <p>Nay, altho this Discourse between <hi>S—h</hi> and her is trumpt up now, we never heard of it during her being with Child; for had she but said she had had the least expectance of that tenth of <hi>June,</hi> she had then been more narrowly watched about that time.</p>
            <p>Considering the whole Nobility of <hi>Ireland</hi> intended to be here, as well as the Countess of <hi>T—l,</hi> for what one reason made her be here at the Labour in <hi>June,</hi> and they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared but against that in <hi>July;</hi> what reason I <note place="margin">News-Letters.</note> say can it be, but that she being one of the Confederacy, had other private notice than what the other Nobility had, who knew not the juggle; this yet appears plainer, for that this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>T—l</hi> was heard to say she should be back in <hi>July;</hi> which must be certainly on the account of knowing the Queen would come sooner; and if she had stayed as long after the 15th of <hi>July</hi> as after the 10th of <hi>June,</hi> it is very improbable she would have said thus: But this was in a discourse far from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of the P. of <hi>W.</hi> which was the reason she so unwarily threw it out.</p>
            <p>And it appears throughout the whole, that all well-wishers to the Cheat were by private designs in and about the Town and Court, on purpose to be called to make their appearance for witnesses; and all others, not friends to such designs, were so decoy'd, that there was not so much as one party on whose testimony we can reasonably be expected to rely; so that by the total partiality of the Choice, there appeared more design than chance.</p>
            <p>The Bishops being put in the Tower, is generally thought, was then against the Kings Interest, but I offer that it probably would have made for his Interest, for the thing was so evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prejudicial, had he not had a private Interest to ballance such certain prejudice, that he could never have stumbled over such an apparent block, and what was this private Interest but by their being out of the way, as I shall shew, he and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates were the better able to bring this Cheat about; and consequently, get more to his Cause by the Birth of a Son, than he could lose by the hatred and prejudice he incurred from so Imprisoning the Bishops.</p>
            <p>And this was done that they might amuse and confound all such who they thought would Eye them, so as to tell again what they had observed. The King offered to the Bishops a thing he knew they would not (nor could they by Law or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science) conceed to, which was to read the Declaration, resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to make the refusal Imprisonment, tho' such a harsh judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was never before design'd for so small a Crime; which strange Revolution, he supposed would so distract all those that designed to watch the Queen, for those so designing, must consequently be friends to the Protestant Religion, and so were desirous of finding out this Cheat. Thus, I say, they design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly confounded all the watchful, whose thoughts being so ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with that unexpected act, and little thinking the Queen would pretend to come so long before her reckoning, and so soon after her going to St. <hi>James</hi>'s, that before they could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect themselves from the Consternation, the Child was popt on them.</p>
            <p>A further advantage by putting those Bishops up, was that they hindred them from being present, on whom we so much relyed on; for they being all Courtiers and Favourites, it could not be supposed but some of them would have been there by Chance, or would have come on notice of some honest Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who no question would have called them without the Kings leave.</p>
            <p>And they knew these honest Bishops, had they by chance or notice been in the Chamber, would not have been satisfied with what these others have been, but boldly ask'd to see more than they designed to let them, and had such a certainty of it, in which no <hi>deceptio visus</hi> could possibly be couch'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis urged, that on giving a small recognizance, they might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42098:7"/> have been free, and so being <hi>statu quo,</hi> might have been at the Labour: To this I answer, that this reason did not occur till after the delivery; for had they before seen this design, they would have prevented by giving that Recognizance, which for many reasons excerting this case they ought not to have done; for they little thought the Queeen would have come so soon, but expected to be out before the 15th of <hi>July</hi> to attend.</p>
            <p>Tho there had been obstinacy in the case, and that they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully went to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the design of sending them was purely in pursuit of his declaration, and not about the birth; I say here (notwithstanding their being in the <hi>Tower)</hi> he might, if he had desired as he ought, to have had 'em to be present at the Labour, have sent for 'em up under a strong Guard, and so let them return.</p>
            <p>The King cannot pretend that he was ignorant what men and women we would rely on; if he did not know, he ought to have enquired whom we would chuse for our Trustees; if he did know we had chose them, he knew those were the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and to imprison them was the designed way not to let us have 'em.</p>
            <p>Had we chose Partial violent men, he might have excepted, but these men he knew were without any spot or blemish of designed falshood, and who he was satisfied would have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented the truth to the people, had it been the Queens Child, and by their words we would have been concluded.</p>
            <p>It cannot be objected that 'twas immodest, being Males, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there were younger men, and of looser Characters.</p>
            <p>Had the Queen been really with Child, no question but we should have had the Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently urged to be there, all the time of the bigness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> although the Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> was not sent for till <hi>June,</hi> the Dutchess of <hi>Portsmouth</hi> was sent for in <hi>April,</hi> and came in <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They cannot pretend that they deferred asking her by reason of bad weather, for our Summer had been long begun, and their Summer so long, that it was almost over, so that the Seas were free from the Storms of Winter on either side.</p>
            <p>The Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> was the party, the Law particularly directs should have had notice of the Queens bigness, when she intended to lie in and where, not by hearsay, but by notice from the King; and whom it was their Interest to have present, for the many inconveniences that would otherwise accrue. And as there cannot be one reason found, why the Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> was not there, so there cannot be any offered, why the Princess <hi>Ann,</hi> (in a manner Heir Apparent) had not the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to view her Belly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if not for her own sake, yet as deputed by her Sister, but more wonder that she was not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly desired to be at the Delivery. First, being one, as it were, of their Houshold and Family, they might do it by word of mouth, and so the failures of an Embassador cannot be urged. Secondly, the Princess <hi>Ann,</hi> for her self, Sisters, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions and Truths sake, had a mind to be there; and she cannot be said to have slighted the least motion of such a Request from the King, but rather sought all means to inspect the Queen when with Child, and be at the Delivery. Thirdly, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple desired her to be there, whom I suppose she would not disoblige. Fourthly, had the King desired it, she was ever so Dutiful, as she would now have Obeyed in so Just a Request; and which the King ought to have made. But on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, all unfair and circumventing Ways, were tryed to hinder their lawful Inspections, tho' highly for the Kings Interest, had it been a true Birth; but they would have certainly been found out in a Cheat, had such search been, and therefore 'twas his Interest to evade.</p>
            <p>But mind, although there was an Embassador continually residing, she was not Invited till almost the 10th of <hi>June,</hi> so late, that they knew if she made never so much haste, nay, come away without any preparation of Equipage; nay, had she come Post, the Child would be Born.</p>
            <p>She ought to have had longer than a months notice, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider of going, preparing an Equipage suitable for one so long out of the Land, and Heir Apparent, and to honour the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> now lest the first Woman who was to come, and did, about the 10th of <hi>June,</hi> as I hinted before, should have a Girl or dead Child, and that the Queen should be forced to stay till the next Womans Crying out, yet could not the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess have been here, neither in so short a time as the 15th of <hi>June;</hi> before which day, no question all the Women expected, and consequently, the Queen must before then pretend to be Delivered.</p>
            <p>It is urged, that being a case concerning the Princesses Right, why came she not without sending? To this I answer, that they ought for their own Interest to have sought her coming; and that it had been for many obvious reasons improper for her to come without inviting.</p>
            <p>Notice ought to have been given that the Queen did depend on her, being in <hi>England,</hi> long before the 10th of <hi>June,</hi> that all who did desire to come, or send Inspecters, might be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; first, because the first reckoning must give her more certain signs 'twas the true one, and for that people that are uncertain of their reckoning, ought to have all provided against the first; and this ought to have been one of the provisions, being much to their Interest.</p>
            <p>It was their Interest more than ours to have her there, we had an Heir against whom none could except, if they brought one to disseize her, they ought to have prov'd their title as the Law requires; and the Princess <hi>Ann</hi> would have been absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a good concluding Evidence, in whose word the people had rested satisfied. She is a just Woman, and would not have prevarricated out of Affection to the Princess of <hi>Orange</hi> her Sister. She would not have represented it to be a true Birth, had it not in relation to her self, for the Princess having no Children nor like, 'twas impossible she would harm her own probability of Succession.</p>
            <p>She had had Children, and the people could not think she could be cheated by Ignorance in such businesses.</p>
            <p>And she had saved the trouble of mens being there, and by that means they had had the liberty to make the Birth more publick, because in the publickness consisted their Interest. The Kings introducing men was only to make a fair pretence of covering her, and not letting the Woman see what is usual in true births. Notwithstanding knowing the Princess was not there, and allowing she could not be there; it ought to have been publick to extremity, but on the contrary it was private to a nicety.</p>
            <p>That altho it may be urged, that the King knowing the truth of the matter, would not trouble himself to seek after Witnesses, folks in the right being negligent, and knowing the truth will bear out it self.</p>
            <p>Yet there is a difference between a ngeligence or non-endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to publish, and a wilful and designed acting to keep it as private as was convenient for such a design.</p>
            <p>But the Queen disdainfully laught at and slighted these things, which all wise people saw were absolutely necessary: So that her disdain of her Belly's being tryed by witnesses then, was but a pretended height of Innocence that she would have thought that she knew herself so clear of the thing she was charged with, that she scorned to submit to the touchstone or scrutiny; and her crying now is only to shew a pretended de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of what can never be recalled; and in fine, both so well timed to their purpose, that they have no other face but design, like a young Heir or Widdow, who perhaps had designedly contributed to the death of the person they seem to grieve for; but were not Miracles ceas'd, would keep their eyes dry at all adventures, lest some out of pity should restore what they seem to grieve for.</p>
            <p>Did they leave out such Protestant Witnesses from being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be present at the Delivery, because they were afraid such Protestants would deny they saw such Child born of the Queen, notwithstanding they really had? No sure, for that no sincere Protestant, according to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and of good life, (many of which might have been found) can be thought would be guilty of such a wilful denial, it is on no account whatsoever allowable by their rules, but is notoriously allowable by the Popish Priests and Doctors in these very cases; for which I can alledge, if it were needful, a great many Authorities from their own writings.</p>
            <p>Her Reckoning, according to her own account given after the Birth, has so much of sleight pretence, that I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what made 'em so faultring; for it was not with the Queen as usually with other Women, since her Husband lay with her within such a time but twice, and she stands by it the Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42098:8"/> was one of those times: Whereas other women bedding their Husbands every night, cannot, nay it is almost impossible they should tell which night in the week it was; but certainly had they laid but two nights in such a space of time, above a month being between those nights, and it afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> at at the Delivery, appeared it was the first night was the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and not the second; here, I say, the Woman must have had more certain motions during the time of her Bigness to make her satisfied the first night was the Conception, than that the second was, inasmuch as the motions of a real Conception gives all along more certain and satisfactory signs, than that which afterwards proved false; for a month makes a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in such things; and the Queen having bore several Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren before, cannot be supposed to misunderstand her conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so much as to be ignorant of her Conception and coming.</p>
            <p>Nay further, add to her own skill, the advice of the Doctors, with whom she often discoursed the matter: But indeed she gave so confused and uncertain an account, now 'twas one time, to which she herself brought objections; then 'twas another time, and that likewise had its objections: Tho in fine her Doctor supposed the first time to be the Conception, for it seems this Woman who had this Boy the Queen resolved first to try, and if that failed, make use of another Reckoning: And the Pallat-bed showing unprepared, was that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he might be delivered in the great Bed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for their purpose. This excused the resolution in what house she was to be delivered; being delayed so long and so suddenly assumed, that Princess <hi>Ann</hi> could not possibly have had notice, and came up in the time between that and the Labour.</p>
            <p>On this pretence was the very Childbed linnen deferred, and not brought by the maker thereof till after the Birth, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, the Queen must of necessity have more certain Emoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the first and consequently, expected to come about the 10th of <hi>June,</hi> all Women doubtful of their Reckoning, do provide against their very first Expectation, for fear of any fright or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident; and though they come commonly a few days before, yet are reckoned to go out their full time too, a few days making no difference; yet was not this Linnen so much as provided, or ordered to come home, till long after such expectation, which is so gross a design, as none sure can attempt an excuse for it.</p>
            <p>Had she indeed mistook her reckoning, so as she had gone longer, it had lookt less of design, because then all parties after notice of such expected time, would have waited about Court, and been ready in her Chamber on the first notice, and then the Confederates could not have done it; but this is so corresponding with the rest, that it makes a great figure in this muster of presumptions against them.</p>
            <p>There was an obvious danger in neglects, had she been really with Child, and therefore she would have been very considerate, fear would have made her earnest to provide against such dangers, but when there is only a pretensive expected danger, and the providing preparations against them would do the design harm, by drawing people about, thinking she was near her time; here, I say, such necessary preparations were purposely neglected, for she knew she could receive no bodily harm, or real detriment, as usually attends Deliveries by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects.</p>
            <p>All other steps being Suspicious, this of her coming in the day time, does somewhat confirm it; for if it be owned that she was not with Child, and that Women really with Child generally come in the Night, then the Queen being but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedly with Child, could not have the Child, till after the true Woman had really brought it forth.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Births of persons are properly proveable <hi>a Principio,</hi> by seeing the Child come out of the Womb; this is, what by their strange and close actings, render'd utterly incapable of any proof that way, and must be referred proved <hi>a posteriori,</hi> that is, lying in a month, seeing the Child took out of a Bed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are all such irregular, inconsistent, impossible, and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous actions to prove a real birth, that they absolutely, as we shall shew, prove the contrary.</p>
            <p>Now when I talk of a publick acting, I don't mean that they should have exposed her Majesty in the presence of dull doltish Teagues, villanous Jesuits, and bigotted flattering Courtiers; but a select company of grave, wise, and just persons, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too for their own interest, all Causes going the better for the prudence and honesty of its witnesses; would not the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of <hi>Denmark</hi> been better believed than the Marchioness of <hi>P—,</hi> a <hi>Sandcroft</hi> than a <hi>J—, &amp;c.</hi> this had hindred the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies of the obstinate, and that medley of folly and beastli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that is corrosive to all Chast Ears.</p>
            <p>Nor do I mean that all parties whatsoever that desired it might come in, for in this case those that could be the most boysterous and rude should have filled up the Chamber before any Lords could come, or forc'd 'em out had they been there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; therefore there ought to have been a selection, and if so, Religion, Truth, Repute, and Honesty, was far greater to be sought, and was a better accomplishment than Titles of Honour without.</p>
            <p>Now he made a choice, but of what? the wilfully blind, the partial, the timerous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now would not any Thief, if had minded to rob, and might choose the house he would take from, would he not choose to pilser from before the blind, or the weak and timerous? Such was the parties, such the occasion, such the choice.</p>
            <p>It is the Custom of <hi>England,</hi> that if a woman be seized in Fee simple, and marry, the husband shall have such Lands for life, and after her death, if he ever had a Child born of her now alive, or being born was heard to cry: Now can it be supposed but she being with Child, that the husband will not look after her, and see all things are prepared, that she may not endanger herself, and consequently the Child, and so he lose the Estate; nor must he have her brought to Bed privately, for the Child may only live to cry, which how will he prove, but by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a great many Witnesses, and those too, <hi>bonos &amp; legales,</hi> for shall the Wifes word, or only a profligate Midwife, and that too, perhaps, against several hundred Circumstances be taken?</p>
            <p>Suppose the <hi>French</hi> King were a Protestant, and the <hi>Dauphin</hi> yet to be born, who must put by the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> a great Papist? Ought the <hi>French</hi> King to call only <hi>Protestants,</hi> or those leaning that way, to the Delivery? No sure, for they are disabled there, as much as <hi>Papists</hi> here, and so not being proper Witnesses, could not have been believed.</p>
            <p>Well then, if such caution must have been used, although the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> nor any other, had not in the least doubted the <hi>French</hi> Queens being with Child, and were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly satisfied thereof, what greater caution ought there to have been used by our King and Queen, who were positively charged, during the bigness, and before the Delivery, with evil Designs?</p>
            <p>All that can be alledged against the Queens having all <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> in the Room, is, that such as help'd might have done the Child harm, and they, as well as those that lookt on, might both joyn and swear they saw none. This is a vain Supposition; for first, they might have had <hi>Papists</hi> about her, letting but <hi>Protestants</hi> look on, since the truth was as perceptible by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, assistance not conducing to satisfie them more, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king people ever the better Witnesses. Secondly, 'tis so unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable an objection, that so many good people should have joyned in a denial of truth, that we do not alledge it against these ill men and <hi>Papists;</hi> I hope, if they will say good <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> would deny the truth, we may in this Case say ill <hi>Papists</hi> uphold a Lye. All I have against them is, that they have out of fear and partiality hid their Sentiments; for if a Juggler calls me to say, Did you see me pull a Knife out of my Mouth? Here if I say yes, for fear of his displeasure, I do not give my Sentiments that it was not real; and though what I say is Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to one knowing the matters, <hi>viz.</hi> he seemed to aver it, as Jugglers do such things; yet my partiality, fear, and desire, of having truth concealed, is little better than having falsly sworn: And a <hi>Papist</hi> being disabled by our Laws, for being a Juror in a Cause of two Groats, his disabillity in this Case must be greater.</p>
            <p>Suppose there could be no more alledged than heedlessness, from the Kings not having such as the Realm could depend on, and by Law capacitated. First, it is strange as he should be so unnatural, as to let his Child be hereafter involved in the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of an obscure Title. And secondly, 'tis a Crime of the highest nature, wilfully to bring a Civil War on the Country, after whose welfare he was so immediately obliged to seek.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42098:8"/>
            <p>'Tis frequent to Murder the next Heir for Ambition, but to do it for Religion and Godliness, to break all the tyes of Law and Nature, certainly the Doctrines that allow such a thing, do likewise pardon the breaches they go through to act it, and make the Wickedness meritorious; that what they call good may come thereof.</p>
            <p>If to attain such a height is then the perfection of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, certainly it is worse than Atheism, and must not only era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the very principles of Love and Nature (which the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists have in Extraordinary measures) but in owning a God, hurl him down to mingle among the fallen Angels, as one pleased with such monstrous Impieties.</p>
            <p>They were charged before the Child was born with Cheating; Not Guilty is by them Pleaded: Now the matter being to be decided at the Birth, would not any man that has a thing to prove, and can make choice of Witnesses, take those of greatest reputation, and such as were known to be impartial; would not you, if a will was made in favour of you against the heir, see that the Witnesses that subscribe be of good repute, for it may be the Heir may put you to the proof of the thing, only because in Judgment he knows the Evidence of your Witnesses wont be taken; but to chuse such as the Law and Nation dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow of, can be no otherwise presumed than a Counterfeit, they were privy to, and connived at, what others would have detected; yet notwithstanding, forcibly and with a strong hand, to set up such Witnesses against the Law of the Land, and his own Interest, is certainly nothing but what all honest men will protest against.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King thinking the birth required help, like the King of <hi>Englands</hi> second, sets forth Menaces in his Memorial, or Letter, to Cardinal <hi>D'Estrees,</hi> at the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had call'd in question the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>'s Birth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Sentence he draws in by the Head and Shoulders, being a thing very improperly squeez'd in, thinking to cut the knot he cannot untie. It being observable, that three several Embassadors went and came about the time of this pretended Delivery; and I am very credibly inform'd, that by this means, and this way, went all the Intelligence to <hi>Rome,</hi> and Communications on both sides; the reason of this privateness, being lest Envoys to <hi>Rome</hi> so very busie at that time, would have look'd suspicious. And it cannot be suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, but the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi>'s Embassador knew all the Juggles, so expecting the Child would be Born at the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> and not in <hi>July,</hi> as gave out; he begins his taking leave in the latter end of <hi>May,</hi> that as soon as the Child was born, he might be gone, to give Intelligence to <hi>Rome,</hi> without the noise of an Envoy.</p>
            <p>The Childs being sent to <hi>Richmond,</hi> separate from the Queen, was certainly done that she might be eased from the trouble of a forc'd fondness, which being so continually to have been done (had the Child been always with her) would have at last grown so nauseous and awkard, that notice must have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thereof, from the difference between a continual forc'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and a free and real one; sure her fondness should have been great, not only as it was her only Child, but the great hope of attaining that which she so passionately desired, yet notwithstanding she used all means and pretences to have it out of her sight: This is very like a pretended or foster Parent, but far from real and natural fondness, and which no Woman (considering 'twas an only Child) could have undergone, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering circumstances for a real love, suggests so many fears, passions, and desires, as that it may be neglected, thinking none can look after it so well as she herself, and a thousand such things, which all the worldly Interest can never suggest; the one being the motive of Policy, the other of a passionate, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal love and fondness.</p>
            <p>The Doctors weighing the Milk of the Woman now Wet-Nurse, shews that they ought to have seen the Queens, e're they gave their opinion for it not to suck; for the same reason they refused the Milk of other Women, they must have refused the Queens, if at all refused; but they did not refuse such Womens without seeing it, therefore not seeing the Queens, they could not refuse it nor speak of it; so that this is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to what I said above, relating to its being brought up by hand, which was not, as is pretended, by the advice of the Doctors, but the private interest and design I have here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated.</p>
            <p>The Queen going to <hi>Windsor</hi> presently after the month was out for the Air, shews that she might (had there not been the design I set forth) have gone to lie in there: Since it never was pretended that the King had any business to dispatch here in Town, that required his stay all <hi>April, May, &amp;c.</hi> whereby he might be hindred from being at the Delivery: But it is noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously apparent that the conveniencies of <hi>St. James</hi>'s, and the Convent adjoyning, are not to be met with in this Kingdom again, for the more easie conveyance of such an Imposture into the World.</p>
            <p>The next thing that occurs is the manner of taking the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, for when a matter is contested, such a man charging, and such a one denying, if the party denying examines Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, the Opponent ought to have liberty to cross-examine such witnesses on Interrogatories, or pertinent questions to find out the truth, for a man may by equivocation and reserves, lay a story together that shall <hi>prima facie</hi> make for one party, but when sitted and explained, shall make for the other: And this cannot be a good Examination, for the Witnesses produced by the King were not in the state and circumstances other Witnesses usually are, for in other matters if a man speaks a truth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making or marring the party he is examined for, such witness shall be safe, and the party whose cause is so prejudiced can take no revenge: But here any man that should throw out, or that should urge a suspicion against this birth, he is sure to be ruined, persecuted and gibbeted.</p>
            <p>'Tis a good exception against a Witness to say he has a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on the party for whom he is examined; but 'tis a greater to say that the Witness has such a dependance, that he has not only his livelihood by him, but his life hangs on the arbitrary will of a man whose depravedness can put to death without Law or Reason; certainly such Witnesses fear shall be enough to keep his tongue from saying any thing may anger the Tyrant: And his Evidence cannot be allowed of who hopes for rewards, or fears punishment, according to the matter he shall depose.</p>
            <p>Is it not strange now that they should infer from them, and force men to credit 'em as much as if they had been regularly capacitated Witnesses; certainly if they could have gotten re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, as well as these irregular and partial Evidences, they would have done it, that they might have insisted the more warrantably on the creditableness of their testimony.</p>
            <p>There can be no stress laid on that Examination, where the party for whom a Witness speaks partially, can protect such witness against the other he abuses, so that the party wronged is not capable of taking due satisfaction. If the King does but pretend, tho never so absurdly, that they abuse him, he can revenge, but the other, tho never so apparently wronged, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have redress. The King is Defendant and the Papists main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers; so his Majesty sits as Judge and the Papists Defendants, are examined for themselves, and none to interrupt them.</p>
            <p>I urge that the King ought not to have been there, and that his presence awed the Deponents to speak partially for him, and so over-awed the Auditors that they could not interrogate, which had been the only way to have found out the truth: But that liberty was not given to any present, whereas they ought to have been desired to put their questions; it not being conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the Auditors, on many obvious reasons, to Interrogate, without first leave had of the King.</p>
            <p>The circumstances of all parties could not oblige the Witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to bethink themselves, as in other places of Judicature; for let it have been what it would, so it was for the Kings Interest, there were rewards, and no fear of being found perjured, and prosecuted for it.</p>
            <p>They could not avoid coming when sent for by the King, tho they knew that they could do him no service, if they spoke truth, and their plain and ingenuous thoughts. And when they were come, fear and the awe of his presence kept them from saying any thing that should harm the King, and consequently themselves.</p>
            <p>The King ought not to have sent only for such persons as were at the labour, (and perhaps sent not for all them neither,) but should likewise have made publick Proclamation, that all parties whatsoever who knew any thing concerning the Queens bigness and delivery, should come and depose on Oath such their knowledge: And that he promised to indempnifie, and not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42098:9"/> molest 'em for any thing whatsoever, if faithfully and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally delivered. I must confess it is not proper for parties to summon witnesses against themselves: But in this case, where it must be supposed there was no guilt on the part of the King and Queen, he ought to have seen if any thing to the purpose could have been said against the birth, that he might have vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated it fairly to the World.</p>
            <p>Perhaps it will be asked why I insist on the Depositions, as evincing the forgery of the birth, considering the King not only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the choice of those whom he called to the pretended delivery, but had likewise the opportunity of leaving out of those, the bold and most conscientious at this after-examination. And therefore it cannot be thought he would bring any that should prejudice the cause they came to evidence for? In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer whereto I shall offer but this, The King chose, as near as he could, the most timerous and partial to be at the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; if there were by chance any in whom he had been mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and would not swallow the trick, this second choice purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed such parties out. But supposing the Witnesses to his hearts desire, let's see what use may be made of their Evidence; but first I shall mention a story applicable to this; A Gentleman of <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> some few years since dying, his Laundress pretends the deceased was indebted to her in such a summ, and produces a Bond for the same, subscribed (as appeared) by the deceased; the heir putting her to the proof thereof, she produced two Witnesses, who swore that they saw the deceased actually sign and write the name subscribed, upon which a Verdict going to pass for the Laundress, it happened one present asked the Witnesses if the man was then living, and writ it himself, or was he dead, and had his hand guided by another? To which, after many shiftings, they answered, as was true, that they had put a Pen into the deceaseds hand after his death, and so subscribed the name. The instance is very applicable. And further, since we had not the liberty to Interrogate the Deponents, which was the only way, as in the case above, to have found out the truth, and so being not allowed that right, the Kings pretences are not only false and inconsistent, but all is covered over with an equivocating and partial Evidence.</p>
            <p>Those Witnesses which have positively denyed or equivocally concealed some things which were material, varnished over others, and not giving their true sentiment of the pretended Labour and Delivery, are as ill as those that added things which were not done, as Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> saying she delivered the Queen of that Child, all the rest, I say, are with her equally for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sworn.</p>
            <p>If such an Examination as this shall be suffered or insisted on, so as to claim the like subjection of belief as is due to depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions regularly taken, then farewel all future redress; for to have Depositions regularly taken, there ought notice to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven some convenient time before, with the names of those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons intended to be examined: There ought likewise to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited plain and intelligible Interrogatories, not intricate, such as confound and intangle the Examinant, by equivocal and catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words; which Interrogatories ought to be drawn up by an impartial hand: And further, such Witnesses must be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by an Examiner no wise byast or concerned in the cause. And lastly, such Witnesses must be neither dependers, relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor parties; nor must Papists be admitted as Witnesses in any cause whatsoever: It is a usual Interrogatory, Have you been instructed what to answer thereto? Art thou any Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Servant, or Depender? Shall you get any thing by the partys overcoming for whom you are examined? Such Witness is utterly incapable and incapacitated, and his Deposition must be suppressed.</p>
            <p>Again, the Opponent hath the liberty to examine these Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses over again by apt Interrogatories, through which the Examinants will be so sifted, that unless they down-right deny the thing asked, and so for swear themselves (against which can be no remedy) they can find no wicked Evasion, no Equivocation: which some people, devilishly infatuated, think no Perjury: This is the way which the whole wisdom of man has invented, without Racks and Tortures to find out the truth, and which cross Examinations are ever executed in doubtful matters, or when the Witnesses are suspected to be partial.</p>
            <p>But the Examination at the Council Table is not in the lest corresponding to these methods laid down, but contrary in all respects.</p>
            <p>'Tis such a way, such a method, as perhaps was never seen in the World before. Was there ever forty two persons called before Authority, to witness for a matter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Non-Criminal as charged, and such Deponents not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one question, when there were present several Bishops, Nobles, Lawyers and Aldermen, who ever took it for a Cheat to this very hour, and consequently, were so unsatisfied at the taking of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Depositions? Yet were not any of these suffered to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogate to those obviously Imperfect and Abrupt Sentences; for had such Depositions been as full as they ought to have been, and which their own case (if the Child was the Queens) requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the truth, could not have been so concealed as it is, but had either carried the Princes Birth beyond questions; or, have so exploded the Villany, as they should not have had an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to hold by.</p>
            <p>Therefore these matters laid before the Council on the <hi>22d</hi> of <hi>October</hi> last, and here Animadverted on are not Depositions, nor Examinations legally taken, with relation to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the Cause; but a medley of Proceedings a new manner of taking Evidence, purely Calculated and cut out for an old Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant design, that has lain unpresidented since Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, and <hi>England</hi> nere saw such tricks since Popery left us.</p>
            <p>So that these pretended Depositions are no more than Affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits drawn up as each had before consulted for their own safety, not to incur the Kings displeasure; so having the liberty of saying what they would upon one side without fear, interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or scurvy knotty Questions; they spoke not what they ought and which would consequently have made their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties displeased, but what might keep themselves in their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties favour.</p>
            <p>What was the Solemnity of bringing these Judicial Acts into Chancery, but to give 'em a varnish of Regularity, as if all had been managed as Causes are in that Court, whereas never was Decree made in Chancery in favour of so notorious a Cheat on Credit of a bundle of Affidavits, dictated by none but partial Deponents, for a Cause wherein they were over-awed by the powerfulness of one of the parties, <hi>viz.</hi> the King. As for the Witnesses saying in Chancery that their Depositions were true, we will grant it <hi>(W—s</hi> excepted) but not that they are the whole truth or Impartially delivered, and the more true the matters of Fact therein contained are, the weaker are all their proofs, and the stronger are our exceptions to the Childs Birth, because their pretended proofs are not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to its being a Cheat, but corresponding to such a Birth; and frivolous, and inconsistent to a true one, wherein it had been their Interest to be publick; so that these Depositions or Affidavits being the very utmost plausibility they can put on it to evince its being a true Birth, this plausibility is meer pretence which does not amount to any thing for their cause. Nothing is therefore said against the truth we offer, but mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters truly consistent and agreeable with the position we lay down, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> Birth is a Cheat. For what reason did Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> appear at the Court of Chancery in so mean a habit, (going at other times richly attired, but now) with a Green Apron, a short tattered Scarf, and as her habit was changed so was her Speech and Countenance; certainly it was, that she might seem to that great Concourse as a poor silly Creature whom it was impossible their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties would trust to in so great an Affair, one who seemed not to have the sense to be capable to manage it.</p>
            <p>If all Births are equally capable of having such proof as whereto can be no exception, then I Appeal to the whole World, if the Evidence they have given, though admitted, can amount to such proof as might have been had; nay, to any proof at all, had it been true it was capable of proof: And as it was capable, 'twas their Interest to have made it so In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contestable, which 'tis not to be supposed but they would have done. A Father may forfeit the Right a Child has in Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, by neglects, as in this very case, and yearly claims; but when such a Father, being notoriously known to have made such neglects, yet shall pretend he has not, and going to the Vindication thereof, his Evidences are not only in the whole Inconsistent and Contradictious, with each other, but seperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in themselves, weak and frivolous, all bearing the very face of a Trick; such an Evidence, I say, on the part of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not in the least giving the lye to the Opponents asseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42098:9"/> must so far carry the matter beyond suspence, that it amounts to a Confession of the Guilt, and claims Sentence against its self.</p>
            <p>If you come to particular Objections and Questions, as did you see the Child Born, you can find no better an answer to it, throughout the Depositions, than this, <hi>viz.</hi> I saw it taken out of a Bed. To this again is an obvious Interrogatory: Do you think it was conveyed there in a Warming-pan, or otherwise? To this not a Word. If you ask if any saw her Milk run out, plainly and perfectly from her naked Nipple, to this they answer, They saw Milk wet on her Shift. And so of the rest, giving in the whole not one good or reasonably satisfactory answer. And now I shall come to consider every part of the Depositions by themselves, as Printed by Authority.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THe whole the Q. D. was pleased to say, no Oath being administred, is worded with very great dissidence; she gives no matter of Fact for, or against the Birth. Is it not strange for her to be at a Labour, and yet not lay down one Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance among so many that ever occur? Certainly she saw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing agreeable to a Delivery, for she would then have spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, since sure none will say she was partial out of love to the <hi>Protestants</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her Majesty says she staid till the Queen Consort was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of the Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> I say so too, there was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, and a Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> such as it was. Now the truth of its being a Prince, Lawfully Intituled, depends on the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery: Child Births are obvious, and things the most capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a plain Testimony and Explanation (as to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances) of any human Affair whatsoever; and if Q. <hi>D—</hi> does not prove what they designed, and what is capable of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable proof, were it true then, it must be taken <hi>pro confesso,</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> is an Imposture.</p>
               <p>The Affidavit runs thus, <hi>viz.</hi> That when the King sent for her to the Queens Labour, she came as soon as she could, and never stirred from her till she was Delivered of the Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> which is no more than thus: That the King sent Mr. <hi>Nicolas</hi> to me, who said I was desired to come to the Queens Labour; I came to the Labour to which I was sent for, and stirred not away till that Labour had produced a Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> Now what this Labour was to which she was sent for, and the Prince it produced, we must look for among the rest; and that they can give no Facts in Evidence, but what imply, and are consonant to a sham Labour, I shall anon make appear.</p>
               <p>Perhaps it will be wondred that amoung 42 several Witnesses, Justice should so prevail as to work on them some remorse, and bravely to deliver their plain thoughts, notwithstanding the danger. To which may be offered, there are certainly in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nation 40 persons, that for fear, dependance, or an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Religion, will connive at, or conceal the Truth; forty such were chosen, and that people have frailties is not to be wondred at. None can deny but <hi>Garnet</hi> was Perjured, yet was he Sainted; Equivocation is only another Name for Perjury.</p>
               <p>But supposing most of these not swayed by the aforesaid rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, yet there is a Self-preservation to be considered, when the truth thereby laid open, will not countervail for the risque that is run. Thus, suppose my Lord be a man may fall under this denomination, and had vehement Suspicions of its being all but pretence, yet could not he communicate such mistrust to others before examination, to know whether they would stand by him and speak his mistrusts, if his Lordship should first begin them, so that when they came to be examined, the first of these Impartial Lords, whose part it was to speak, knew not whether if he threw out his Suspicions, the next would confirm them, so that he being but one Witness, could never have hurt the Birth by a Suspicion, but very much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered himself.</p>
               <p>Well then, all the Witnesses have spoken as much for the Kings Interest as possible, and if there are any seeming suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, they are really such as the facts were, and not designedly by them made so. Of this I am very glad, for had the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses shown their Resentments, the <hi>Papists</hi> would have said they were partial, and so not owning the Depositions, would have denyed our suspicions from thence drawn; but the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses being owned by them to have Impartially delivered the utmost they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, then are all our allegations, if rightly drawn from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> sure grounds undeniable, and shall be made use of accordingly. The face of these Depositions, was the best gloss that was possible to be put on such a design; and how lame, weak and foolish it is, you may judge by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going and following Catalogue, the Contrivances that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently seen through it, and which it cannot cover, it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appearing these Depositions are great Evidence for us, they proving that such and such facts being done, are not the real circumstances attending a true Labour, but the usual Tricks and Pretences that are made use of in such designs.</p>
               <p>I am necessitated to displace the Depositions other than as Printed, and shall rank 'em in more convenient order, that we may take our rise from the Conception, and so go on gradually to the pretended Delivery.</p>
               <p>The last Paragraph of Sir <hi>C. S—hs</hi> Affidavit, relates to the Queens Conception, by which I will prove that the Queens first pretended Conception by all the Circumstances which the Deponent says her Majesty gave him, thereof was the only reckoning for which she ought to have prepared, That she came to a day by that reckoning, That the second reckoning which she pretended to prepare for could by her own Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be no expectance in the least, and that both of 'em were the reckonings of other Women.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>C.</hi> says, that the Queen in <hi>December</hi> then last, in Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course about her reckoning told him she had two reckonings, the one from the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Sept.</hi> when the King came to her at the <hi>Bath;</hi> the other the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>October</hi> following, when she came to the King at <hi>Windsor,</hi> but for some reasons rather reckoned from the latter, and then said, that she had gone Twelve Weeks and was quick.</p>
               <p>But the Deponent knew it could not be in so short a time after the last reckoning, nor was it, for the Queen was then gone full Sixteen Weeks, at which time she quickned with her former Children, and accordingly was brought to Bed within Three Days of full Forty Weeks; and it is altogether unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidented, that quickning should be in Twelve Weeks, but Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen as it had been with her Three Children afore, according to the rule of Nature and other Women, what reason had she to set up the last reckoning, that no preparation might be but against that time? but that the Princess <hi>Ann</hi> and every one should look on that, and if they did intend to be at the labour, it must be that in <hi>July</hi> when the other was past, and so suppress the other, which was the likeliest reckoning which by all reasons she ought to have prepared for, and accordingly should have had Nurses, Pallat-Bed, and the Princess, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and been sooner at the place she intended to lye in at: Now I would feign know on what grounds this last reckoning was so undoubtedly stuck to, since it was the false one; why, perhaps they will Answer the certain private reason the Queen had, which thô she then was in Conference with her Doctors as is necessary about it, she neither acquainted him nor ever any body else, nor in truth could have any certain sign to contradict these true ones that have so proved themselves; therefore the private reason of sticking to that which after proves the false one, is wholly taken away by saying it was false and did so prove, and for that she had no pretended nor plausible reason whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; Now that the first was false is evident, for that had she certainly been with Child she wou'd not have been so far from the place intended, a Queen be so far and so unprepared, why, a Citizens Wife would not go cross the Street for danger of her self and Child, but a Queen to be so careless, or suffered to be so, inasmuch as her hurt had endangered a Prince so much sought, is a thing I must confess altogether Monstrous; and further there is as much evidence from the premises, that the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> on which she went to St. <hi>James</hi> was the day which she might as well look for to be her full time as the <hi>12th</hi> following, which was the exact Forty Weeks; First, for that thô some Women come after Forty Weeks, when a Girl, yet they evermore prepare before, or against the Forty Weeks, not knowing but it might come some days before, as this did. Secondly, that Women reckon, thô it be some days afore Forty Weeks, yet they have gone their full time, and sure all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42098:10"/> are prepared against that full time, which is a Week at least before Forty and not have a considerable way to go, a Pallat-Bed in the next Room un-aired, and no body, not so much as a Nurse, Midwife, nor any of skill about her, this is a very great proof that both these reckonings were a design and juggle, for as I hinted before, it is to be presum'd they had several Women, therefore must be prepared in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reckoning, for to take the first which might be a Boy; therefore all these reckonings were but reckonings of the other Women, and intended to be made use of for the first that brought a Boy into the World.</p>
               <p>So having proved, the Juggle of her reckonings, and that this pretence by all its circumstances was Calculated to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a false Child, we shall see what was the next step (lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that of her Milk and Belly till anon) which is from her being alone more than usual, sending all about her away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so well so short a time before bringing forth, the unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredness at the same time they were in, and so show the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity she got by all the Circumstances following, wherein there appears so much design, so many consistencies with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended labour, and so many Inconsistencies with a true one, that none but Jesuited Bigo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s can act, nor any but a design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Papist deny.</p>
               <p>That she attended the Queen when she was last <note place="margin">Pel. T—</note> with Child, and that on the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> last in the Morning her Majesty told the Deponent she was in pain and bid her send for the Midwife, Ladies and Servants, after which she staid with the Queen during her labour and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til she was delivered of a Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> now as to the first Sentence of being last with Child, it had two Faces if she knew, as certainly she did, any thing of the Juggle, here she Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates and refers to the Queens being last with Child of the Lady <hi>H.</hi> when tis possible she might be likewise with her, and if so, then 'twas when last with Child; if she knew nothing of the cheat, then this Assertion of the Queens being last with Child is to be concluded by the latter part of the Deposition concerning the Queens labour; if this Lady had seen nothing before, and we can prove that this labour was fictious, and that she could not see any thing that should give any Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a true Birth, then is the labour and delivery, and being with Child all of a piece.</p>
               <p>Now this being after Eight of the Clock, is it possible that her Majesty, being brought to Bed so soon after, should not have any symptoms but an hour before, and her full time too? That her Majesty should be up and dress'd so soon? For dress'd she must be, otherwise the Queen could have no pretence to send them, nor they excuse to go from her; but go they did, and no question wheedled all away, and she left alone with this one Lady, all gone so far off as not within call, but to Chappel, where 'tis usual to stay a considerable while, perhaps never done so before. And this I insist on, for if it was not usual, they would not have gone on their own heads, but sent away, and if designedly and unusually sent away, we know what they would be at, for it was the greatest help imaginable to their design, and had they staid, would have been Evidence for the truth of the Birth, but their being so sent away, is a great suspicion of the Imposture. Now it being convenient for one to stay for the plausibility of calling the rest, so of all her Gent. this <hi>P. T.</hi> was pickt out, an <hi>Italian</hi> Lady, her own Native, a great Papist, and with whom it shall be supposed (having a great disregard to the <hi>English)</hi> she would certainly disclose sooner than to another, therefore this is more suspicious than if any other, this was the likeliest to be concerned and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted primarily in the business, who being sent away, the Queen was now alone, and none within call or hearing.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>T—</hi> calling Mr. <hi>W—</hi> and he going for Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> and it is observable that the Queen continued some time alone, before Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> came, who cannot be supposed to do any harm to the privacy, and was ordered to send for Madam <hi>D—n</hi> who was at the Chappel; and to give the greater op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to what was to be transacted, the K. being up and drest, was gone to his own side, drawing all the men with him, whereby they were at full liberty to convey the Child out of the Dormitory, adjoining to the Queens Chamber, into her Bed.</p>
               <p>Lastly, had it been any body else but <hi>T—</hi> I should not have so much as suspected, for as there was something to be acted while they had turn'd their backs, so who fitter than this one certainly concerned, being all along of the Queens privacies, a cunning Woman and great Papist, Zealous for the Queens In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, a hater of the Princesses, and no lover of our Country. And this absence of Madam <hi>T—</hi> was done on purpose, that if it shouuld be objected, being such a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that she knew of the Cheat, she might say I was far from the place, when 'tis supposed to be done: But it was she carryed on the feigned bigness of her Belly, so was the properest person to be with the Queen just at the time she cried out, and for her going away it was when a better, <hi>viz. W—</hi> was come.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>D—n</hi> being sent for from <hi>St. James</hi>'s Chappel, found the Q. all alone, who bid this Deponent get ready the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat-bed which stood in the next Room; but that Bed having never been aired, the Deponent perswaded the Queen not to make use of it.</p>
               <p>Now is not this a strange thing, that a Queen on the very day she expected should be so unprepared of a thing the most necessary, and which was so useful that the Queen askt for it: alas, 'twas an easie thing first to carry it so that no body should know where she would lye in, and so to run to this place which had the Pallat removed but a little before, and without doubt by the ordering of one of her Creatures: And all the pretence is of its not being Aired, when it was certainly designed before that it should neither be brought in nor aired, which none that had the charge of preparing the Lodgings for a Child-bed Woman dare have omitted. And here let us take notice, that the first not letting it be brought in, and the next of not having it aired, and so not using a Pallat, was greatly opportunate to the design of this false birth; for it had been absolutely impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to have carry'd the Cheat on by the use of a Pallat: So for the convenience of imposing a false birth, they dispenced with the necessity belonging to a true one. But here it will be objected, if it was so necessary for their design to have her delivered in Bed, why lay she not a Bed all the morn? And then coming in Labour, the excuse of not rising had been plausible. To this I answer, that her rising was of absolute necessity, for by that means, first being drest, and waiters done their duty, she might send 'em away, and so lay the Child in the Bed when all alone. Secondly, to have the pretence of warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, that the Child might be brought in the Warming-pan. And having now shewn why the Pallad-bed was not used, why she rose, why she used the great bed rather than the high, and that these things were not matters of Indifferency, but abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely necessary with such a Cheat, without which it could not be performed, and that they are utterly repugnant and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with a real being with Child; I shall pass on to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the matter of the Warming-pan it self.</p>
               <p>The Deponent further saith, she saw fire carried into the Queens room in a Warming-pan, to warm the Bed.</p>
               <p>The Story about the Warming-pan is so likely and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a thing, and for which the Queen purposely rose to give opportunity for its use when; I do confidently aver, that no Woman so near her time, and having hard Labour, as appears by the Childs being stunn'd and her shrieking, Yet to this very material thing that stands against them, nothing is said no more than as could do it a careless thing thrown in, which amounts to no more than a common Phrase of speaking: As suppose I had been in any room where this Warming-pan had gone through, and having no Suspicion (as it is with Madam <hi>D—n,</hi> who if she had any, dared not to deliver her self) but in common phrase would say (though I see not the fire) there is fire or coals gone to warm the bed. Nothing so common, and I do aver, had Madam <hi>D—n</hi> seen fire, or had the King thought she had, Madam <hi>D—n</hi> would have explained whether she had seen the fire, or how she came to see it; and having omitted it her self, the King being present would have Interrogated. It had been ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely necessary, and I am confident they would have proved it by bringing the party that took up the fire; and enquiring whether she that took 'em up, could swear she carried 'em forthwith to the Queens Bed, and did not deliver it to another. Madam <hi>D—n,</hi> above all the rest, saw the fire, when it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the Warming-pan was with the cover down, which is unusual, and that had it been up more would have seen it, and spoke to it as well as she; but of this, not a word to make
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42098:10"/> us believe there was Fire, but innumerable Circumstances to shew there was not any, this Warming-pan being brought in, no question, from the Dormitories hard by, when not above three or four were there, and those Papists, dependers and well wishers to the Cheats going on, as <hi>VV—, Delabadie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> should warm the Bed (for 'twas she as the Deponent says prepared it) now was contrived, because she was the only proper party that could do it; she knew how to take the Child out, and lay it for the most security, being to produce it again, and so knew where and how to find it, she was the party must help the Queen into Bed, and so knew how to direct and lay her; all this done too, the Curtains drawn and she on the further side of the Bed warming it, or bringing the Child out of the Pan and laying it in the Bed, for the Queen being to lye on the farther side, that side being next the Wall, 'tis evidently proper that none were between her and that Wall, or by her, for that it shall be presumed, that so few being in the Room as but four, Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> preparing and warming the Bed, the Nurse running up and down, Mrs. <hi>D—</hi> and the C. of <hi>S—</hi> was little enough about the Queen to hold her up and undress her, and the Queen with <hi>D—</hi> could not be between the Wall and Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> but properly on that side farthest from it, because it was largest, more proper next the Fire, and that there was not space enough for the Queen, and <hi>W—</hi> warming the Bed to be all on that side. I believe Madam <hi>L—</hi> was not primarily concerned in the cheat, but being a well wisher, would not highten but cover suspicions, and so would not pry nor be busie about any thing but what the Queen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired them, which was enough to say, let her warm the Bed be you about me; but it will perhaps be urged, that they need not have been so private among friends, to this I Answer, that those things which were necessary to be done had some suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them, but always the well wishers were imployed who as much as in them lay would perform their part, but it was absolutely against their Interest to let either well, or ill wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers see the thing it self, for that was a secret ought to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to as few as possible, and is never safe in many Mouths; two may be resolute and close among ten, but more, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly dangerous to their design. None but Papists being there, very willingly let Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> do what she would, the Curtains being drawn, without looking after her, for that they knew whatever Mrs. <hi>W—</hi> did was for the benefit of that Cause which they desired should be brought about at any rate.</p>
               <p>All that is in the first part of this Ladies Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition <note place="margin">C. <hi>of S—</hi>
                  </note> I have spoken to already, in my considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the foregoing Deposition, and therefore desire the Reader if he does not find every particular Circumstance of this Deposition taken notice of, that he would look back to my consideration on those Witnesses Depositions that speak to the like purpose; and trying these by that Test, I question not but that he will be satisfied, that all that Harangue in this Ladies first part of her Deposition, of her being sent for twice to the labour of the Queen, saying, she was in labour, and what that labour was, were all design'd advantages, which I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered in Madam <hi>D—</hi> and so shall pass on to what has not yet occurr'd.</p>
               <p>This Deponent <hi>S—d</hi> says, <hi>That the Queen after having had some lingering pains said, she feared she should not be brought to Bed a great while,</hi> but the Midwife assured the Queen that she want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only on thorough pain to bring the Child into the World.</p>
               <p>Now what can this signifie more than that the Queen thought hereby to shew the little correspondence, agreement, or design she and the Midwife had, and that there was no fore knowledge in the matter; so the Midwife at the crys, to shew her skill, and the Queens mistake, out comes a Child according to the Midwifes Prediction. So that if there can any thing be imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this impertience it seems to be cut out for their present occasion, for all their Discourse throughout is repugnant to one another, even in the most trifling things; like two Rooks that will chatter, contradict and quarrel together on purpose that the third whom they intend to bubble may think they have no correspondence; it will be askt perhaps why the Midwife should pretend to know the Queens Case better than her self? why, to shew that the Queen (who must be supposed to know of the Cheat as well as the Midwife) was ignorant of any intreague whatsoever. But the dispute and its design end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not here, for upon the difference of those two Parties a third must be call'd in to be Umpire, who thô not an Intreaguer yet a well wisher to the Cause; for says the Queen in answer to Mrs. <hi>VV—, 'tis impossible, the Child lyes so high, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Deponent to lay her hand on her Belly,</hi> but not a word mentioned in the Deposition of the posture she found it in.</p>
               <p>This Deponent says further, that a great pain come at past Nine of the Clock, and the Queen was Delivered.</p>
               <p>It must be noted, that after eight of the Clock, the Queen was so well, that the King and all her Servants left her alone (a thing perhaps never known since she has been a Wife, but such a step was very necessary and must be had) so that after her beginning to feel pain, calling people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was not above three quarters of an hour e're she was brought a bed, and yet she Skreems, and they talk of pains, as one that had long and hard Labour; tho nothing is so inconsistent with her being delivered in a Bed covered, none assisting or helping, though many standing by, as in the most easie Labours, and the Child stunn'd, as in the hardest, which I shall explicate anon.</p>
               <p>It is convenient first to shew what are the steps and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the most easie labour; they may be delivered in Bed, the Child may work it self down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not by the pains force the Mother to skreek, for Delivery is a work of Nature, which as they are different, so the hard and the easie are without difficulty distinguished. But what a medley is the Queens being in Bed, according to the easiest Labours, skreeming as at the hardest Imaginable for the time, having none to help her but the Midwife, when even the most easie Labours are generally better provided for.</p>
               <p>Pray now, from what one reason in this Ladies Deposition can it be expected we can believe a real delivery, seeing her own reasons cannot Rationally satisfie herself? If she urges the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Queens Belly, nothing more easie (as I shewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to deceive her. If again her skreeming shall be urged, consider how easie it is to prove any one in Labour and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, if no other arguments are necessary, but to say such a one skreemed.</p>
               <p>Then how came you to say that the Queen was delivered, because Mrs. <hi>VV—</hi> said, when the Birth was over she would pluck this Deponent by the Coat, which was to be the sign that the Queen was delivered and of a Boy, whereby it appears the C. neither saw the Child born, nor whether it was a Boy or a Girl, therefore can be no Evidence.</p>
               <p>But this very saying of the Midwife, that it was a Boy is utterly Incongruous, for no Midwife can see of what Sex the Child is before the Burthen is drawn out without detriment to the Queen, which cannot be thought to be hazarded for her curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osity, therefore the Midwifes Item was by a fore knowledge.</p>
               <p>That this Deponent was in the Queens Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note place="margin">C. <hi>of R—</hi>
                  </note> while the Queen was in labour, and saw the Prince of <hi>VVales</hi> when he was taken out of the Bed.</p>
               <p>These Circumstances do not in the least prove that a Child came out of the Womb, but they might produce one out of a Bed where they had layd it, this being no more to the purpose than if she had said she has since seen it taken out of the Cradle: The question is, did you see the Child born, and the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition is nothing to the purpose.</p>
               <p>But here you will ask, if the King knew they could give no better Answers, why did he bring it on the Stage, since the matter was better thought on before than it could be expected it should now? I Answer, that the King thought he had Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Spectators, or at least they were such who would not or dare not in the rehearsing it add any thing, and so he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the World might have been as well imposed upon as the Witnesses were with the same thing, thô supposing these Witnesses not to have wilfully added Circumstances which were not, but admitting all was carryed as in the Depositions, these very Circumstances are great Indication, that 'twas a Cheat, and can have no honest intention under them.</p>
               <p>That she stood by the Queens Beds-feet when <note place="margin">C. <hi>of T—l</hi>
                  </note> her Majesty was delivered of the Prince of <hi>VVales;</hi> now this Deponent being not Circumstantial, she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the labour the rest speak of and can say nothing to the purpose; on the other side it is not to be expected from a Papist a well wisher to the Cause, and aw'd by the Kings
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42098:11"/> Presence, that she should say any thing might endanger the pretended young Prince.</p>
               <p>That she was in the Queens Bed-Chamber <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hen.</hi> Lady <hi>W—</hi>
                  </note> a quarter of an hour before her Majesty was Delivered, and standing by the Bed-side saw the Queen in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and heard her cry out much; here is nothing to do but to consider the manner of the labour, and whither this crying out much was consistent with her labour, as it appeared hard or easie, and what in the whole be thereon layd.</p>
               <p>In the first place she owns she was in the Chamber but a quarter of an hour before the Birth, and so did not see the Warming-pan, nor whither all the other steps were feazible, nor was she there when the Queen called to a <hi>Protestant</hi> Lady whom she had a mind should be absent, and cry'd pray go, take my Lord Chancellour out with you, for I am very hot, and must be uncovered; so she and my Lord went out and the Door was immediately shut after them, but whither the Queen did uncover (thô there was at that time none but friends) I could never hear of; so taking this Lady not to be one of the Confederacy but a well wisher, we shall shew that her crying out much was inconsistent with all the other signs, which were those, that as well as they could manage them, implyed an easie labour, for to have no likelihood, or qualm at full time till an hour before Delivery, and that labour not to come on by frights, nor other accident, then to be Delivered in a covered Bed, thô against Interest and conveniency, and to have no occasion of help, all these signs of easie labour, and yet to skreem and have the Child black and in Convulsions, manifest signs of hard labour, is such a medley as never was heard of. It is not enough to say such a one is in labour because she skreeks, 'tis no Answer to the Question, but did you see her Face? Was she pale? Was her Eyes and Cheeks hollow? Did she look ghastly, amazed, and in the anguish and high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulsions of a Soul really in that torture she seemed to be by her cries? This no question the Deponent would have spoken if she could, which had signified not much, and as it is 'tis nothing to the purpose.</p>
               <p>Went with the Queen Dowager to the <note place="margin">Mrs. <hi>A—n C—y</hi>
                  </note> Queen Consorts Bed-Chamber, and stay'd till the Queen was Delivered, and saw the Prince as soon as he was Born.</p>
               <p>Whereby it appears she was not there sooner than Queen Dowager, and consequently saw no more than she, for it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears, that the Child was conveyed into Bed, and the Queen therein too and covered, resolving to let the Queen Dowager, and all that came with and after her to see no more; and as for her saying the Queen was Delivered, implying she saw it, is no more than seeing a Child taken out of the Bed, nay, they did not in reality see so much, but by the Midwifes saying she had it from thence.</p>
               <p>She was not at the Queens labour, being her <note place="margin">C. <hi>of L—d</hi>
                  </note> self in Child-bed, but was almost constantly with the Queen while she was with Child, and hath put on her Smock, and seen the Milk run out of her Breast, and felt her Belly; so that she is sure she could not be deceived, but that the Queen was with Child.</p>
               <p>All that can be said is, that this Ladies Deposition implys no more, than seeing Milk drop from that part of the Queens Shift about her Breast; for should any persons see Milk drop through a Womans Shift about that part covering her Breast, would they not, (knowing she was Married, that she had born Children, was reported to be with Child, and had an appearance of a great Belly) believe the Milk run out of her Breast; as suppose a Man had wound a Napkin about his Leg, and should say it was cut, and blood should run through this Napkin, might not you say, that you see his cut bleed, whereas perhaps his Leg was never cut, but that a Spunge full of blood was bound underneath, and by the pressure it ran out; but if on a mature and deliberate Examination on Oath, I explain my self no otherwise, and that my words cannot possibly mean any more, then 'tis all to no purpose; for a Spunge as before being fill'd with Milk might at the time the Queen designed to impose on the Deponent, be conveyed next her Breast, and by the pressure would yield drops enough for that purpose, but afterwards carried down into the Bed, and thô the Smock were pulled off, yet the C—ss be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But to conclude this Argument about the Milk I must add, that I do know several Women at this time who have Milk in their Breasts, that have not been Pregnant this Twelve Years, and which may be drawn down, so as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out, whereby 'tis evident none of the Depositions can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on which relate to this subject.</p>
               <p>As for feeling her Belly, I must confess I should be glad to have these Questions Answered. <hi>viz.</hi> How long since, was you desired by the Queen to look on it, for satisfaction against those reports, or had you any thing to do about it?</p>
               <p>To these necessary Questions the Deposition gives not any Answer; for first, it might be so little a while after Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that no regard is to be had, especially since the words im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply no more than a view by chance, that this sight of the Belly was not near the Queens time, appears by the Deponents lying in when the Queen did, therefore could not for a considerable time before put on the Queens Smock as she lay in Bed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great inconveniency to her self and her Majesty, might easily counterfeit a bigness that was necessary to deceive the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, considering the time she pretended to be gone with Child.</p>
               <p>That from a little before <hi>Easter</hi> last, till the <note place="margin">Madam <hi>B—y</hi>
                  </note> Queen was brought to Bed, she saw her Majesty put on her Smock every Morning, by which means she saw the Milk constantly fall out of her Majesties Breasts, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served the bigness of her Belly.</p>
               <p>Now as I said before, this Lady was not called to do any thing, or purposely required to take notice, so that she might Swear but only by a glance, about which time the Queen might secretly wet her Nipple, or perhaps it might be the effects of the Spunge; so that it was by no other means than by shifting, which being to be done so quick, nothing can be depended thereon; and as to the bigness of her Belly it can be no more, than that she saw the Queens Belly as others did when she was drest, and the words import no more, than as I may see a Woman go along the Street, and by observing the bigness of her Belly, say, that Womans, with Child and near her time.</p>
               <p>That she was constantly with the Queen <note place="margin">Dame <hi>I—a W—e</hi>
                  </note> when her Majesty was likely to miscarry, (which she gives no reason for her believing) and that she has often seen Milk on her Majesties Breast, (this point is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any new Circumstances, therefore what I said before is a sufficient Answer) and this Deponent put the After-burthen in a Bason of Water, this action gives very just cause of suspition, being done before the Doctors viewed it, and no doubt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a discovery, that it had not the Natural warmth it should have, which the Water would prevent from being found out afterwards, had the Doctors been never so inquisitive.</p>
               <p>As to Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> the Midwifes Deposition, <note place="margin">W—s</note> divide it into two parts, the one is of things obvious, and proved by other particular persons, as her being call'd by Mr. <hi>W—,</hi> her making the Bed, her telling the Queen she doubted not, but that it was her full time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I no ways doubt nor except against, otherwise than that these things might be, and yet consistent with a false Birth. But secondly, as to feeling the Child stir, or seeing the Milk otherwise than with such Circumstances, Mental reserves and Equivocations, as I have mentioned before, and that she Delivered the Queen the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1688. of this Male Child, I do utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept against and disallow. 'Tis obvious that the first particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are such matters of fact as might really be, and no proof of a Childs being then really born, nor that they cou'd not be done, had not a true birth been. But the second is her saying she delivered the Queen at that time of that Male Child, and I hope I have sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made appear, by all the foregoing circumstances, how utterly inconsistent it is with common sense, that this should be a true Birth, and what Reason can be alledged why this Inconsiderable Woman utterly incapacitated by Law, and upheld by such great Persons, should have any Credit given her, tho' she swears positively when there is so many convincing Reasons to prove the contrary; especially when 'tis to be considered that all our Laws, Liberties, and Religion, were aimed at in the design.</p>
               <p>Now for the Counterpart, the Deputy of this <note place="margin">D—dy.</note> Forgery comes, Mrs. <hi>D. She did not miss above six days all the nine Months and that at several times, by</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42098:11"/>
                  <hi>reason of Sickness: And that on the 10th of</hi> June <hi>last, she was sent for to the Queen: That the Midwife told the Deponent, that Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately on the next pain the Queen would be Delivered, which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly she was, &amp;c.</hi> Throughout all this long Deposition there is nothing new to be taken notice of, being matters that show no Evidence of a real Delivery, and thô it might reasonablely be expected this Deponent might see more then the rest of them, as well as Mrs. <hi>W—,</hi> because she kneeled down at the Beds-side, yet she says not the least word to the only material Evidence can be given in such Cases, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Childs coming out of the Womb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That about</hi> December <hi>last, the Queen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">La—y M—ss of <hi>P—s</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>being like to mis-carry,</hi> (which she gives no other reason for, but the Queens saying so) <hi>she offered some remedies which the Doctors examining, were approved of; that she saw the Queen Shift her self several times, and generally the Milk, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times her Smock being wet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This seeing the Milk generally, might be no otherwise than the Lady <hi>L—d,</hi> as to see it drop through her Shift, as in common speaking, and she sometimes seeing it wet on her Smock, was after it was off, she might see that part of her Shift next her Breast wet; for there's only this difference, as suppose I was in a Tent, or Booth, and the Rain drops through, here I may say, I saw the Rain, thô perhaps it might be Water thrown over on purpose, and not come down from the Firmament; so that here if the Lady <hi>P—s</hi> is drove to speak, and comes to Confession when she shall be confront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, she can come off with this, that she only meant so; and therefore shall any assume any thing from the very words, that according to Genuine construction bear a sense, that will stand with a false pretended labour, and that the words as I have Genuinely construed 'em, will bear out my Lady from being forsworn; well if the words are so as is evident, then by reason she is not forsworn, they are true, and the truth stands on our side.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That sometime after this Deponent went into the Country, and came not till a few days before the labour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to be noted, all that were immediately concerned kept out of the way, thinking that their being oft with the Queen would be urged, as their being concerned more than ordinary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That she was in the Room at the time of the Queens Delivery of the Prince, which this Deponent saw; And this Deponent avers this Prince to be the same Child which was then born (and which she saw taken out of the Bed.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all this she says no more to the purpose, than the rest on this Subject, the pretended Prince having no other Title to it, but because Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> pulled him out of the Bed, after the Queen had squeakt, and this Deponent saying nothing that may be a further proof, I shall proceed to the next.</p>
               <p>That she saw the Child taken out of the Bed by <note place="margin">Lady A—</note> the Midwife, and given to Mrs. <hi>D—dy,</hi> and that she saw it was a Son; and this Deponent has seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times seen Milk upon the Queens Smock, during her being with Child.</p>
               <p>But suppose she can, on further Interrogation, truly say she saw the Milk fall distinctly drop by drop, out of the naked Nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I see not what can be from thence raised, but that it was drawn down, as I have shewed it, to be usual: Of all which things the King, Queen, and whole party, knowing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, ought to have exposed the Child and Queen before Credible modest Persons, that it might have been seen to come out of the Womb, which is the best proof and answer could be given to those noises they were so well acquainted with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Deponents Servants seeing Queen D—r</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lady B—</note>
                  <hi>Coaches in St.</hi> James'<hi>s, at an unusual hour, asked the occasion, and was told the Queen was in Labour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note how private the Labour was carried, lest some might hear it by chance, that were not sent for, who might be too prying, for this Lady lives just by St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and tho' a great Catholick and Favourite, Lord <hi>B—</hi> being a Minister of State) yet neither she nor her Servants, who 'tis to be supposed were up and down the Streets, being about Eight of the Clock, heard, nor saw any thing like it; certainly this precaution was not for nothing, since I am sure truth needs none.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the Deponent came, she found Mrs.</hi> W—ks <hi>sitting by the Bedside, with her hands in the Bed.</hi> The hands in the Bed is the principal Evidence of a great many, which was certainly to keep the Child from smothering; and indeed, that brought forth more plentifully than the Queen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Queen asked the Midwife what she thought, who assured her Majesty, that the next great pain the Child would be born; whereupon the King called the Privy Councellours in, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (that they might be dispatched, and not stay to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y about) <hi>the Queen shreiks, and the Prince was Born.</hi> A very pretty account, a Child must be fetcht out of a Bed, made Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> likely to ruine all <hi>Europe:</hi> And this, by the assistance of a few Witnesses, who can give no reason for it, but several Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences against it, and yet one single Womans sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing so, a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man disabled, particularly from being a Witness in Civil Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and yet to be the maker and raiser up of a Successor, by an Implicit Faith on her Words; and to make it as sure as possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, no body came to Court but what was sent for, and the men were not called in till they were ready, and all things or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to make it appear as fair as could be contrived.</p>
               <p>Now had there been fair dealing, they ought to have sent for honest people, not their own Creatures, and those to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as soon as they come; this had shewn they needed no time.</p>
               <p>Suppose a man had murdered another, the Constable comes to search, the Murderer prays the Constable to stay till he calls him in, so he burys the party he has Murdered, Cloaths and all, lays the floor again, washes away the blood, so when the room is dry, the Constable is admitted: But which is worst of all, our Privy Councellours had not the liberty of looking in that very place where they knew the Cheat lay hid.</p>
               <p>This yet is further against them, that of all the men sent for, 'twas so ordered, that the Doctors, (who could judge better of these things, or the truth of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, than either Men or Women) not one was time enough to be at the Labour, though all pretensively desired.</p>
               <p>Lastly, there is one thing more with relation to Mrs. <hi>VV—</hi> who would intimate thus: That presently, as soon as she cut the Navel-string, the Child cried: the Navel-string was cut in Bed, <hi>ergo</hi> it must by this reasoning cry in Bed. But this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent <hi>B—</hi> says, that she opened the Receiver (so that the Child was out of Bed) and not hearing the Child cry, and seeing it a little black, she was afraid it was in a Convulsion Fit; so that Mrs. <hi>VV—s</hi> Intimation is designed, as may be gathered from what I spoke before to the matter of the Navel-string, and would have it be thought that the Child cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sooner than really it did.</p>
               <p>But perhaps, some may urge that I contradict my self, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving urged before, that the Navel-strings not being cut, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the Child from crying, so that if that hindred, the Navel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string was cut, and yet I own it cryed not thereon.</p>
               <p>To this I Answer, the Child might have dyed in this smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering fit, had it been kept un-cut much longer, whereby being much indisposed, that time after the cutting to the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was only to recover it self.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Deponent did not follow the Child into the little</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mrs. <hi>C—e</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Bed-Chamber, but stay'd with the Queen, and saw all that was to be seen after the Birth of a Child, that is an After-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and bloody Clouts;</hi> but nothing of the Womb or Belly, of which we should not have only heard from her, but from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for she cannot be supposed to see alone.</p>
               <p>As for her saying, she saw all that was to be seen after the Birth of a Child, this is not well exprest, for it should have been thus, <hi>viz.</hi> is or can be seen by the Body of the Queen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For if this Inspection was not on the Body, which had it been she would certainly have spoke of, but this implying nothing but bloody Clouts, the Midwifes bloody hands, After-burden, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Clouts were certainly those which were used about the true Woman, which might be easily conveyed, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately into the the Queens Bed, and as for the bloody hands, 'tis so easie to be done, that it cannot possibly be urged as a certainty against a strongly presumed false Birth; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 'tis very partial and contradictory, for as the labour was not like the usual and common labours, that is, I mean on Pallets, in Chairs, or the Bed turned down, so as the Womb is apparent: What was seen after relating to the Queen was no sign of any Labour or Delivery she had really undergone,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42098:12"/> but indeed there might be signs, that might be of any others Labour, as Clouts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this Lady could not say the Queens Body was the occasion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Deponent says he found the Lord</hi> Craven <hi>wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E. <hi>M—on</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>at the Queens Bed-Chamber door, which was then shut, just after the King opened it, and called the Deponent, and Lord</hi> Craven <hi>in,</hi> but what to do, why, truly to send 'em out again) <hi>for they stayd not in the Bed-Chamber, but he sent 'em into the Dressing Room:</hi> Now thô the King held some Discourse with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent as follows, yet the Deponent saw nothing, for had he (being so particular in every thing else,) he would have spoke to this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Deponent asked his Majesty how the Queen was, who Answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Deponent, you are a Married Man, and so may know these matters, the Water is broke, or come away, or to that effect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, that the Water was broke is a thing depending only on the Queens saying so, for there is not one speaks a word of it, nor indeed was there any body in the Room but Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> when 'tis said to be; so that it depends wholly between the Queen, Mrs. <hi>W—s,</hi> and the Kings saying so.</p>
               <p>Note, there is no certainty in the Water breaking; for sometimes it breaks before the Labour; but the Queen must not do so, if she began she must go through stich, for had she stayed so long after it Eyes would have been about her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All the Company were call'd into the Queens Chamber, where he heard the Queen groan, and presently after several loud Shreeks, the Deponent heard them say the Queen was Delivered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now was there ever so little seen at a Womans Labour, as for a party to be at the Beds feet, no body between him and the Party Delivering, and yet he see, nor know, nor give no other reason why she was brought to Bed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whereupon the Deponent stepped up to the Bed-side, and saw the Midwife put her Hands and Arms in the Bed, and fetch a Child out (as the Deponent believes, for that he could not then see it) and gave it to Mrs.</hi> Delabady, <hi>which the Deponent after saw in the little Room, &amp;c.</hi> In all which the Deponent saying nothing new, but what has been sufficiently Answered before, I shall leave him and proceed to the next.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Says nothing material, but that the King said the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E. <hi>H—n</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Queen came according to her first reckoning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Women do not know certainly their reckonings, but come contrary to all thoughts or expectation, but the Queen to know her reckoning to a day, which after proving the true must certainly in all the time of Conception and bigness, have given her more Items of it than the other, but she never prepared for it; but I hope I spoke fully to this Head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>Deponent <hi>S—er</hi> says no more, than <hi>That she was</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S—er</note>
                  <hi>at such Labour,</hi> as the rest, and as for Circumstances she speaks none, knowing no more than what Twelve before had and recounted, <hi>And that she went with the Child into the little Bed-Chamber, and took a warm Napkin, and layd on the Childs Breast, believing the Child was not well;</hi> an expression of a slight qualm that will pass over, which is the very consequent effect of not cutting the Navel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Deponent neither saw the Midwife nor Queen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E. of <hi>M—rt</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>but heard the Ladies say</hi> (another hearsay, prime Witnesses) <hi>the Queen was brought to Bed;</hi> and following the Prince into the little Bed-Chamber, he saw him in the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a new born Child, where is the Latitude of this Answer, new born is promiscuously used; now we dont question but it appeared to you new-born, but that it was above an hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Deponent by the Oath he hath taken, believes him to be the Queens Child.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think there is not a more Arrogant presumptive line in the whole Book, except his Brother <hi>M—y,</hi> by whom as he is out done, so it may be said by both, that the Scotch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has out done the Irish.</p>
               <p>Certainly none ever spoke so boldly without giving some reason or pretence, thô never so Incongruous, being a Man who had never seen the Queens Milk, Belly, nor any thing before the Labour to induce him to it.</p>
               <p>Behold a Man of the same Character, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <note place="margin">E. of <hi>M—y</hi>
                  </note> and Circumstances, that had less reason if possible to Swear, <hi>yet he verily believes, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is alive she brought the Prince into the World that very Morn. being the 10th of</hi> June <hi>last;</hi> to speak to it were superfluous, for 'tis Answer enough to it self, thô indeed 'tis of as much weight as the major part of the Depositions.</p>
               <p>That she came not till after Nine, <note place="margin">La—y <hi>So—a Bu—y</hi>
                  </note> and thinking the Queen in no strong pain went into the next Room, but after a while hearing a noise, and being told the Child was Born, she run to the Queens Bed-side, and heard the Queen say to the Midwife, pray Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> don't part the Child.</p>
               <p>Whereby it appears, she saw not all the steps that had been made, whereby she might have Judg'd of their falsness, but came after Nine.</p>
               <p>The next thing to be considered, is the not cutting the Navel String, wherein lies a great advantage; first, it kept the Child quiet, and from crying in the Bed, or Warming-pan, for it has been experimented, and there appears great reason in the thing; for why does it not cry in the Womb, but because the Child is in its <hi>prima Materia,</hi> and as a Child crys not while fastened to its Root, its <hi>prima Materia,</hi> or place of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; so we see the Flowers never spread nor bear, thô never so deep in the ground till they come above; so a Child, thô out of the Womb, yet having the same Ligature Chain still fastened to him while in the Womb, which by a Natural Ordination of Nature does keep 'em from opening the Mouth, and this yet appears more if you consider, that the Child has not any occasion of his Mouth, for he receives nourishment by that as we by the Mouth, and till he was deprived of that he could not do any Office, that the Mouth is Instrumental to; so that notwithstanding 'tis an impracticable thing not to cut the Navel String, yet they passed that over being indeed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do it for the advantage of keeping the Child quiet; and, secondly, by this means they shewed the After-burden in a more Identified manner of a late Birth (which they were obliged to) than had the Burden been parted, and not left fastened to the Child, for had they cut it before the blood would either have run out, or retired, and made that part from whence it went cold, and much unlike the other.</p>
               <p>Well, then having proved it necessary and highly convenient not to cut the Navel String, for that they might shew it as new Born; they endeavoured to confirm it by doing a frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous unusal thing of giving it three drops, thereby intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that if the Child had been long Born they could not have fetcht fresh blood, when as I have shewn before, that the Burden is made of parts capable of retaining blood, and that of warmth when laid in a warm place; and for that an After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden does remain in almost the same plight for some con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable time after the Child is Born, and more especially if it be not parted. Notwithstanding, I say 'tis dangerous, but that was only to the Mother, a Creature hired and rewarded, yet 'twas absolutely necessary to the Cheat; and as the String not being cut, was the reason of its not crying, so it was of its blackness, and being kept so long stupifyed and smother'd in the Cloaths.</p>
               <p>As to the Queens reprimanding the King for not being by her, is to shew, that if some object that the Queen might cheat the King, whom they think would not do his Children so much harm, the Queen having not that reason, might do it without his consent; but to shew that she desired no such thing, is ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent with the King to be always about her, which no doubt is a great security to the unbelieving Protestants.</p>
               <p>But why went Mrs: <hi>D—dy</hi> away with the Child, before the After-burden come away, seeing the Midwife had as much need of attendance then as before? Why, truly there was but two of them, and should any else that knew not the Cheat, or been privy, they might have opened the Child to those parts of his Body which might have given some Suspicion, but Mrs. <hi>D.</hi> who knew how to shew the freshest, and conceal the other, run away in such haste with the Child, that none might take notice what <hi>W—s</hi> did about the Queen.</p>
               <p>Well then, 'tis owned, she not cutting of the Navel-string, was the occasion of its blackness: that blackness being contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the long while it was out of the Womb, and almost smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, not for any hard labour, for the blackness and stunning comes so, yet it must be from a weaker, and a more extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, long, and painful Labour, than this can pretend to be.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42098:12"/>
               <p>And it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> appears, that this blackness proceeded from its being so long out of Womb, and the Navel not cut: And that it was not hard Labour, for then the Child would not have so suddenly and clearly got over it as two hours, which seemed but which he was refreshed from an Inconvenience and Indisposition, of being not duely enlarged after its being taken from the Womb. And further, that the Child had been long from the Womb, (as I am credibly informed) by the slimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almost dryed, is evident: for it was so long as two hours cleansing, which no Child taken fresh from the Womb could be, but as this was, bak'd on.</p>
               <p>The Deponent had the Honour to wait very often on the Queen in her Dressing-room and Bed-chamber, and hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes seen the Queens Milk, as well as when this Deponent hath put on her Majesties Smock.</p>
               <p>So then, the occasion of seeing this Milk, was not a designed thing for to Inspect her, or do any thing about her, but a thing by chance; just as the Queen was pleased to give the occasion her self (which you may be sure was not so far as to her preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice) and the Deponent could not look further, wherein might be made use of that Artifice I spoke of before to the Countess of <hi>L—,</hi> for no other appears by this Deponent; and had it been otherwise, they would have said, out of her bare naked Breast, without any covering, and that she look'd on it a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable while, and that it came out drop by drop, though, as I said before, Milk may be drawn down. And that this could be nothing but a glance, is apparent from the action then, giving her occasion, which must be in Bed, the Curtains drawn, and as quick as may be; perhaps the shift just put over head, and the other put down to come off at her feet, lest she should take Cold, which is dangerous when with Child.</p>
               <p>This Deponent says not one word to the <note place="margin">Dutchess of L—x.</note> purpose, but that the Queen shewed the Deponent her Smock, which was all wet with Milk. Now we allow of this, and will subscribe to the belief of the Fact, being nothing but what may easily be done, and yet no Evidence, as I have sufficiently shewed before.</p>
               <p>That she was not at the Labour, but remembers that at a time when the Queen apprehended she should miscarry; (of which, neither this Lady, nor the Physician, nor any of the Witnesses, give any sign or reason, but that the Queen told them so.) And the Physicians made her Majesty keep her Bed for that reason, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which being no matter of Evidence, I shall proceed to the next.</p>
               <p>The Deponent heard the Queen cry out, <note place="margin">Mrs. P—se.</note> being in great pain, and saw the Midwife hold up the after-burden, which no doubt was from the same Womb they had the Child, and can be no Evidence that either was the Queens.</p>
               <p>That the Deponent Immediately after took away all the foul Linnen hot as they came from the Queen, and that for a Month after her Majesties lying in, the Deponent well knows by the washing of her Linnen, that the Queen was in the same condition that all other Women use to be on the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
               <p>All this being no Evidence that can be relyed on, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer is not necessary, for none of the pretended signs of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery were easier to be counterfeited than this of the Linnen.</p>
               <p>That she was several times in the Queens <note place="margin">Mrs. <hi>Ma—l</hi>
                  </note> Bed-Chamber when she Shifted her self, and hath seen her Smock stayned with her Milk, and does in her Conscience believer her Majesty was with Child, both by her Milk and Belly.</p>
               <p>Here is proved what I urged against the others, <hi>viz.</hi> that being in the Room when the Queen Shifted is no Argument, that they saw either the Queens Belly, Breast, or Milk drop out thereof, for that this Lady was there very often, yet saw no more than her Smock stayned, and I am assured the Queen is as free with this Lady as any at Court, which appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s by the Deposition, for that she was sent for, but came not, being sick, so knows nothing of the Labour.</p>
               <p>That she often saw the Milk of her <note place="margin">Dame <hi>Is—We—h</hi>
                  </note> Majesties Breast upon her Smock, which the Queen was much troubled at (as to this I have spoken already) and that she, the Deponent did once feel the Child stir in the Queens Belly while her Majesty was in Bed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Deposition is expressed with all the Roman Catholic caution as might be, the only thing in it that seems to be of any weight, is feeling the Child stir in the Queens Belly, which being mentioned only in general terms, amounts to no more than that it was through the Cloaths, for if it had been otherwise, she had certainly said so, and it was very easie to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon her belief in so nice a business as that, especially when it may reasonably be considered to be done on purpose, that the Deponent might be made use of upon any Questioning of the pretended Prince.</p>
               <p>That she saw the Milk often on her Majesties <note place="margin">Lady <hi>P—w</hi>
                  </note> Smock (which I have sufficiently Answered) and often saw her Majesties Belly, so as it could be no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She did not see the Belly naked is evident, because she speaks not of it; so that this seeing it must be after some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner, and what more correspondent with the words, than by the usual seeing Women with great Bellies, which we really think to be so by the outward appearance.</p>
               <p>That the Deponent was called into the Q. <note place="margin">Lord G—n.</note> Bed-chamber, but could not get near the Bed, but stood by the Chimney; there the Deponent heard the Queen cry out several times, and that the last cry was much greater than the others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this Lords Deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being only for show, to make up the number larger, and very little to the purpose, I will spare the Reader and my self, the trouble of any particular Answer</p>
               <p>The first part of this Affidavit, is only that the <note place="margin">Coll. G—n.</note> King called them into the Bed-chamber, after he with several Lords of the Council, had waited about half an hour; whereby it appears, they dared not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach till the King called. Immediately after, the said Lords and this Deponent were in the room the Queen cryed out ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely, and said, Oh! I dye! You kill me! You kill me! Then presently Mrs. <hi>D—n</hi> made this Deponent the sign that the Child was born.</p>
               <p>It would amaze any sober man, to consider what strange sort of Evidence this is to prove the Birth of a Prince, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for next Heir to the Crown; I shall not say one word by way of Answer to it, there being not the least Argument to prove what 'twas printed for, since no body can allow the Queens crying out to be satisfactory Evidence.</p>
               <p>That he waited on her Majesty the Queen <note place="margin">L—d <hi>F—m</hi>
                  </note> Dowager to St. <hi>James,</hi> and led her into the Queen Consorts Bed Chamber, and finding the Queen in pain the Deponent went into the next Room, from whence the Deponent heard the Queen cry out several times, and a very little after the Deponent, and Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil were call'd in; that the Deponent called Mrs. <hi>D—</hi> into the little Bed-Chamber, where he saw the P—as a Child newly Born.</p>
               <p>This Lords Deposition, as well as several mentioned before having nothing new for Evidence, but what has been already sufficiently Answered, I shall pass over, as also the Lord <hi>Cr—ns,</hi> Sir <hi>St—F—x,</hi> E. of <hi>M—ve's,</hi> E. of <hi>Pet—h's, A—l's,</hi> E. <hi>Su—d's,</hi> and Lord <hi>Gef—y's,</hi> all which lay the stress of their Depositions upon hearing the Queen cry out, and seeing the Child foul likewise (as the Chancellour says) Reeking; as to the former, none can pretend 'tis an Argument the least stress in the World can be laid on; and for the latter I have clearly demonstrated before the Child may be brought from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning Convent, and yet appear as they have Deposed.</p>
               <p>The Deponent was present when the Prince <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>W—ly</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Wales</hi> was Born.</p>
               <p>But now it will be askt if no other Circumstances were, why did he assert he was at a Birth? To this I Answer as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he having nothing but suspitions could not do it, and knowing not whither any would stand by him, but must be delivered up to the Anger of a Prince; neither indeed could be have done any good in saying so, for what could he have asserted more than is obvious, and what all wise Men, as well as he perceive; so that the not throwing out such words is a preservation of himself, Estate and Family, which althô had run the risque could have done us little good, for that the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances are as strongly suspitious every whit, as if he had said so, for it could but have added at best one more publick to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42098:13"/> our party, who is already of the opinion in private by the wording of his Deposition; for that being a Physician he ought to have brought Circumstances, which in his opinion were feasible, and his not giving any of the Birth is a great Evidence against it.</p>
               <p>The Deponent saw Mrs. <hi>Del—</hi> bring the Child from the Midwife, and saw the Child before he was cleansed.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Question is, did you see the Child Born? which has no other Answer, than seeing one bring the Child from the Midwife; as to the seeing the Child before twas cleansed, suppose it had not been cleansed till this time, does that argue, that because he saw it in its filth, 'twas Born but a Minute since, nay he does not here make any Summary or Recognition as from what he could see he did in his Conscience believe it but Born three Minutes since, for thô it was excusable in Lords, and somewhat less in the Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, yet was it highly requisite for the Doctors to speak to this, by reason of the more right distinction to be presumed from them than others, whereby it appears they perceived it, but concealed their sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents for safety; and it behoved the King to remind the Doctors, that they spoke of this more particularly, for that it would have gained credit from them rather than from others; like as a Lawyers Opinion is of more validity in Law than any other Persons: why then was so material a point smother'd when Interest call'd, but that they could not speak to it, so as to make for the King? We (the said Deponent, and the other Physicians) did take two drops of blood from the Navel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string, which remained upon the Child, and gave it in a Spoonful of Black-Cherry-water, as the Queen Commanded.</p>
               <p>So then this frivolous thing was not by the Doctors order as Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> and her Assistants cry, but by the Queens, which Corroborates what I have proved before, that this was only a thing designed to make shew of a true and late Birth, and so (like the consciously guilty,) prepared suspitions.</p>
               <p>After this the Deponent saw the After-burthen entire.</p>
               <p>So we say, that an entire Burthen was, but to say it came from the Queen is nonsense, but agrees with ours, that having their choice to be sure it should be of a healthy Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who should get a sound Child, and a sound After-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then are consequences, but to apply it to the Queen is absurd and inconsistent, for as she nor he were healthy, so could not they have a sound Child, or sound After-burthen; so that every word, and all throughout the Book (three words of Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> excepted, <hi>viz.</hi> I Delivered her of that Child) make for us by the most Genuine, free and unforc'd construction, and make nothing for them even with the most partial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction; for what can this mean of the After-burthen, having not proved it her Child, would he say this is her Burthen, if it was hers it must not be entire nor sound, if the right Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it must be sound, as the Doctors says.</p>
               <p>The Deponent came not till Mrs. <hi>D—</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sc—gh</hi>
                  </note> was by the Fire, so that having seen nothing of the Labour, thô he ought to have been there, and about Court all the time of the Child-bearing; of what would he intimate by all this? <hi>He found the Queen in good condition, but weary and panting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And no question she seemed as bad as she could, yet this was to one who saw the reality through the pretences, which were so weak to him, and the real strength so apparent, that he affirms she was in a good condition, which is a great Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboration to ours.</p>
               <p>And saw the After-burthen Reeking warm, but was it so Reeking and warm as you can assert according to your belief and sentiments, that it could not have been taken above a Minute from the Womb, this had certainly been to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, which neither the Doctors nor the King were ignorant of, and would certainly have been urged could he have done it, which he examined and found sound and perfect, so we say too, and yet not be the Queens for the reasons I mentioned before.</p>
               <p>That after a while the Deponent understood, that a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine was mentioned among the Ladies for a certain remedy against Convulsions, it was some drops of blood from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel-string, the Deponent consulted Sir <hi>T. Wi—ly</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Physicians, and to satisfie the Women they allowed of it, there being as they conceived no danger in the thing.</p>
               <p>Here's not a word of their own order, desire, or advice, but they only allowed of it to satisfie these Ladies, there being as was conceived no danger in the thing, so that Mrs. <hi>W—s</hi> and <hi>D—es</hi> false assertion proves the design on 'em.</p>
               <p>That she told the Deponent she had <note place="margin">Sir <hi>W—VV—ve</hi>
                  </note> Milk in her Breast which drop't out.</p>
               <p>But the Deponent neither saw the Milk it self, nor any circumstance to make him think so, which his Zeal for the Cause would not have let slip, being more to the purpose, if he could, than any thing throughout his Deposition.</p>
               <p>The Deponent also affirmeth, that Her Majesty took such Astringent Medicines, during the most part of her being with Child, in order to avoid Miscarrying, that if she had not been with Child, they must have been prejudicial to her health, and of dangerous consequence.</p>
               <p>It was material to say whether they see her take those Astringents; if they did not, there's no reason but to think she threw them away, for she would not hazard her body when the contrary was so easie, so that there is no more said than that Astringents were made; and if any body had seen the Queen take them, they would certainly have been brought to testifie it.</p>
               <p>Now the very best can be supposed of this thing, is, That the Queen told him that she had taken them, although he mentions it not, which he would, had it been so; but then it would again be ask'd, whither the Queen would tell a lye.</p>
               <p>Upon the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1688. The Deponent was called at his Lodging in <hi>Whitehal,</hi> to wait upon the Queen, being told she was in Labour, upon which the Deponent immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went to St. <hi>James,</hi> and so into the Queens Bed-Chamber, and found her beginning her Labour, it being about Eight of the Clock in the Morning.</p>
               <p>Now this is a gross Insinuation, for that by all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, and account of the time it must be above a quarter past Eight 'ere she gave any such notice, and then it must be half an hour after Eight 'ere he could have notice and come, this I am sure he cannot but be sensible of, and it shall the rather be thought partial, for that he is at least a well wisher whom this Child would not only promote and his whole Family, but he knew he should lose his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent employ should the Princess Succeed, and all this to insinuate that the Labour was longer than indeed it pretendedly was, and to show the timely notice and long Labour she had.</p>
               <p>That the Deponent was in the Bed-Chamber when she cryed out, and was Delivered; now this crying out and this Delivery was just as was before related, for that this Doctor can add nothing more.</p>
               <p>And that he saw the Burthen fresh and warm, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further Explanation is nothing to the purpose, as I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before.</p>
               <p>That from the beginning of <hi>November</hi> last <note place="margin">Mr. St. <hi>A—d</hi>
                  </note> he hath generally every day till the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1688. given by the Physicians orders, Restringent and Corroborating Medicines to the Queens Majesty.</p>
               <p>The Doctors ordering such things to be made, does not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in the least, that she took them, since ordering or preparing to take is never understood administring, and as for his saying he gave 'em to her Majesty, 'tis no more than for an Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary to say I gave such a one Physick when very commonly he never saw him take it, and the words imply no more.</p>
               <p>That the Messenger by whom he was sent for told him the Queen was in Labour, and that the Deponent then received a Note from the Physicians for Medicines for her Majesty, which the Deponent was obliged to stay and prepare, and so came not to St. <hi>James</hi>'s till the Queen was Delivered, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is set forth by hearsay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Deponent saw the Child Naked before it was cleansed from the Impurities of its birth: And suppose it had not been cleansed till this minute, and you were now seeing it, does that argue the Child was born at three quarters after Nine?</p>
               <p>And also saw the Navel-string cut, and come drops of the fresh blood received into a Spoon, which the Deponents ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a little Black Cherry Water, and saw given, by the Physicians orders, to the Child: And afterwards going into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42098:13"/> the great Bed-chamber, where the Queen was Delivered, he saw the After-Burthen fresh and warm.</p>
               <p>We do not at all question, nor is there any asservation, that by the Navel-string he thought it to be Born as pretended, or that by the freshners or warmth of the After-Burthen, 'twas certainly evident, that that Burthen was Delivered but a few Minutes since, for a Navel-string, tho' not cut till two or three hours, 'tis possible the Burthen may yet keep fresh and warm, but 'tis evident that his explanation would have done them no good, but us, and so partially leaves it at large to catch the unwary.</p>
               <p>As for Dr. <hi>B—y</hi> I cannot say more against its insuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency to be matter of any proof, than what will occur to the meanest capacity in the reading it, nay, the setting it forth <hi>verbatim</hi> will show it self more in-sufficient than can be imagined from any explication I can put on it, and to take it in naked with all hear says, and not one expression or asservation, from whence any such construction can be raised.</p>
               <p>That a little before Ten of the Clock <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ro—t Br—y</hi>
                  </note> in the Morning, on the Tenth of <hi>June</hi> 1688. the Deponent was in the Queens little Bed-Chamber at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, where the Deponent saw the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> in Mrs. <hi>La—y's</hi> Lap by the Fire side: the Deponent desired to see the Linnen and Blankets opened in which he was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; which being done, the Deponent saw it was a Male Child, and the Navel-string hanging down to, or below the Virile parts, with a Ligature upon it, not far from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but did not see any After-burthen hanging at, or joyned to it, not being at the Birth; The Deponent asked how long he had been Born, the standers by told him, at three quarters of an hour after Nine of the Clock, the Queen was Delivered.</p>
               <p>And now any understanding person may consider with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, if these frivolous pretences, thô granted to be true, are of any force or validity, but that a counterfeit Labour might be carried on with the appearance of all these Circumstances.</p>
               <p>Those too that give in their Depositions, being for the most part partial, unfit, or illegal persons, and their Examination managed with apparent design and partiality; upon the whole, all reasonable people must conclude, that a true Birth can stand in need of no such tricks; and if it shall be said, that the keeping the Queen covered in a Bed was for Modesties sake, because of the Men, yet, why was there not that freedom and plainness to the Women 'ere the Men came in, for not one of the Women except <hi>W—s,</hi> so much as saw or felt her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Belly. This is what can never be palliated, and thô it should be objected that it is usually so, yet there is not usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally such occasions of plainness, as was at this time, and therefore the next Heir not being present, nor any lawfully capacitated, they ought to have been more plain and exposing; and I hope what has been said will sufficiently convince the World, and prevent any designs of the Papists, in raising up Factions to uphold a pretended Title, which the most partial people in the World can give no tolerable reason should be allowed of.</p>
               <p>O! that they would now consider of their wickedness, repent and prevent it, but the Impending miseries I hope my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and future endeavours shall in some measure prevent, by a detection of the matter, and thereby to make all Foreign Princes however Juggled with, to be backward in assisting, and to slight such wicked, scandalous, and unjust pretences.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:42098:14"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of St. James's Palace</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>